THE GOOD PARSON OF LUTTERWORTH.

In tlie reign of Edward the Third, a crowd of the citizens of London were seen on their way to old St. Paurs. As they hurried along the narrow streets, and collected around the doors of the cathe dral, their loud voices and violent actions, showed that they were engaged in angry debate. It was evident that some unusual event had drawn them from their homes so early on that winter,s morning.

A priest, named John Wycliffe, was about to ap- pear, to answer charges that had been brought against him. As they gathered into clusters the accused arrived, dressed in a plain black robe, with a small round cap on his head. His long grey beard spread over his breast. He looked calm, as though the tumult of the people awoke in him no fear. Passing through the throng, he entered a small ancient chapel, which formed a part of the cathedral, where a bishop and the judges had al- ready taken their seats. The accused was not alone. Two noblemen, clothed in velvet and gold, walked by his side. One of them, the Duke of Lancaster, placed himself on his left hand; the 3 [22] other, Lord Pei'cj, stood on his right. When the popish judges saw the powerful friends who had come to support his cause, tliejL were filled with rage; and charged the two noblemen with being ene- mies to their religion and the king. Provoked by these words, the duke in return threatened the bishop, and soon the whole assembly was in confu- [23] sion, John Wycliffe standing all tlie while before his judges without speaking a word. When the people who were at the doors heard the noise within, they cried aloud against the good priest; then running through the streets to the pa lace of the Duke of Lancaster, the most beautiful mansion in the kingdom, they began to pull it down.

In their rage they committed murder on a person that was passing near the spot. These ignorant people had been told by some de- signing priests that Wycliffe and his friends intend- ed to destroy the religion of the land, and in their ignorance they were driven to these acts of violence.

It was like the scene when the apostle Paul was at Ephesus; "and the whole city was filled with con fusion/, because the idol-makers, who feared they should lose their gains, stirred up the people to op- pose the preaching of the gospel.

Nearly twelve months passed away, and Wycliffe once more stood in the same place, and before the same judges. There was again a great crowd of people ; but they were not then crying out against him, and demanding that he should be sent to prison. Since the pious priest was last there they had better understood his character, and had learn- ed to value his preaching. He was now known to them as the gospel doctor. The people had come to support his cause. They forced their way before the court, and demanded [24] that he should not be hurt/, The priests were alarmed at what they saw and heard ; and though they had hoped to have condemned him, they were glad to let him depart freely to his home.

Is it asked, What was the crime that brought Wycliflfe into such trouble ? The answer is—The pope of Rome had sent three letters, or bulls', as they were called, to England—one to the bishops, another to the university of Oxford, and a third to the king. In them he charged the humble parson with many serious offences ; and he desired that he should be seized and sent to prison, there to lie until further orders from Rome. Was he, then, a teacher of false doctrine, a traitor, or in any other way a wicked and injurious man? No; his offence was, that he was an inquirer after truth, and sought to bring the people from under the power of the monks and friars, who led them astray ; and it was because he thus felt and acted that the pope had resolved on his overthrow. There were at this time in England many thou sands of persons called monks and friars. The monks were those who lived alone or separate from other people ; their houses were called monasteries, or places of retirement; the term friars signifies brothers." Of these latter were the begging friars, who, it is said, swarmed throughout Eng land', at this time. They travelled over the land, forcing their way into the houses of rich and poor, [25] living without any cost, and taking all the money they could obtain. Though they assumed poverty, they were not "poor in spirit nor were they "the meek of the earth. Like the Pharisees of old; they pretended to be better and holier than others, though their lives were full of evil. They ,Haught for doctrine the commandments of men," and de- clared that all who belonged to their order were sure of salvation. When Wycliffe saw the conduct of the friars, his heart was much grieved. The best way to op- pose them he knew would be to write a book against them ; and a book was written in which he called them, ,Hhe pests of society, the enemies of religion, and the promoters of every crime.'' Angry and annoyed at the exposure, they were ready to help the pope in the hope of getting the writer sentenced by the judges to the dungeon or to death. Wyc liffe, however, continued to write and preach against them, and with so much labor and zeal that his health began to suffer. One day, lying on his bed, and, as it was thought, nigh to his end, some of these friars made their way into his room. They rushed to his couch, began to upbraid him for what he had done, and called on him to express his sor- row before he died. For some time he heard them in silence ; then, desiring his servants to raise him up, he cried aloud, I shall not die but live, and shall again declare the evil deeds of the friars.' 3* [26] Alarmed at his courage, tbey fled in haste from the room. When Wyclifife got well, he retired to the little market town in Leicestershire, of which he was the priest. In this place he entered on his great work —that of translating the Bible into the English language as it was then spoken. To give the peo ple the word of God was the best way of fulfilling his threat against the friars. He knew that the Bible was God's great gift to the whole human fam ily ; why, then, should not his countrymen possess it ? To give it to them would be something worth living for ; and so he diligently set about his task. It was a long and difficult work for one man to undertake ; but faith and love carried him through it. The word of God was precious to his own soul ; and he knew that what had been a blessing to him self could be made a blessing to thousands. So on- ward he went in his work, with prayer and patience : and as he went along, he found instruction and comfort for himself, whilst he was providing for the spiritual good of others. Year after year he saw the fruits of his study in- crease : one page and then another were done, un til, at length, in the year 1380, the last verse of the New Testament was translated, and the Bible com pleted in its English dress ! We may think we see him looking upon the pile of writing he had made, then falling on his knees to give God thanks, im- [27] ploring him to bless the truth to the souls of the people.* All books in those days were very scarce and costly, for the art of printing was not then known.

Before the year 13 00, the library of the University of Oxford consisted only of a few tracts, chained, or kept in chests, in the choir of St. Mary,s church. Copies of all books were made in writing; and as this was a slow and careful work, it took several months for one person to write a complete Bible. How different is it now, when a printing machine will produce fifteen to twenty copies of the Bible every hour, and thousands every year ! And then as to the cost. Richard of Bury, Chancellor of England under Edward the Third, spared no expense in collecting a library ; the first, perhaps, that any private man had formed. Yet so scarce were valuable books, that he gave an ab- bey fifty pounds weight of silver for between thirty and forty volumes ! The Book of Psalms, with brief notes written in the margin, was valued at a sum equal to nearly forty dollars of our present money. A copy of the New Testament was sold for thirteen dollars* a sum equal to six months' income of a tradesman, for about twenty-five dollars were considered enough to keep a farmer or trader in those times, when so few of the comforts we now * Copies of the whole or separate books of Wyclifle's translation are still found in public libraries. A perfect and beautiful specimen is to be seen in ihe British Museum.

[28] enjoy were known. But costly as was the purchase, it was cheerfully paid. And great as was the dan ger of those who dared to read the word of God, there were some who bravely met it. Written copies of Wydiffers Bible were eagerly sought after by those who could read. There, in a castle, some rich nobleman might have been seen with one of these written Bibles before him, "in fair characters on vellum. If it had been the twenty-third Psalm on which his attention was fix- ed, it would have presented itself with the follow- ing peculiar spelling and Saxon letters : — pe title of pe xxiii. salm ey pe song of dauid. " pc lord gouernep me. , no ping schal fail to me : in pe place of pasture ye he hap set me. He nurschide me on pe watir of refreischyng : he conuertide my soule. He ledde me forp on pe papis of ritzfulnesse : for his name. For whit pouz y schal go in pe myddis of schadewe of deep: y schal not drede yuels. for pou art wip me. pi zerde and pi stafi": po han coufortid me. pou hast maad redi aboord in my sizt: azens hem pat troblen me. pou hast maad fat myn heed wip oyle : and my cuppe pat fillep me is tul cleer. And pi merci schal sue me : in alle pe dales of my lyf. And pt y dwelle in pe hows of pe lord : in to pe lengpe of daies/, But though a nobleman might be found who could read the Bible, yet from the want of learning, as well as books being scarce and costly, there were only a small number of the people who could pos- [29] sess the word of God. Even some of the nobles and gentry could not write their names; and not many of the common people were able to read. Perhaps not more than one in a small town or vil- lage was learned enough to read and write. We may, then, suppose what was the state of the land when the people had no gospel preached to them, and few possessed the Scriptures or could peruse any book likely to be the means of doing good to their souls. England, indeed, had been for ages without the light that cometh from heaven. Errors and foolish rites, like dark clouds, were spread over the land.

It was at such a time that Wycliffe arose as a light in the darkness; and, like the star that ap- peared over the fields of Bethlehem, he gaided many souls to the Saviour. The numerous books he wrote were spread abroad in the same manner as his writ- ten Bible. He also prepared many sermons, about three hundred of which have been preserved to the present day. From these we learn what were the truths he taught the people.

The priests said that human merits and sufferings, penance and pilgrimages, would certainly entitle them to heaven ; but Wycliffe taught that sinful man could not save himself, and that mercy was only to be found through faith in the blood and righteous ness of Jesus Christ. The priests asserted that im ages should be honored, and that there were many [30] mediators ; but the bold reformer said that the wor ship of images was idolatry, and that saints and angels were not to be prayed to, for " there is but one Mediator between God and men/, He main tained that the church of Rome is no more the head of the churches than any other church; and that the apostle Peter had no more power given him than any other apostle; and for all his doctrines he referred to the Word of God, maintaining that it was the only safe guide to a Christian man. In many other ways he opposed the doings and teach- ings of the priests of the Papal church. Wycliffe did not quite receive all the great Bible truths in all their fulness : it is a wonder that he knew so much at a time when all the land was sunk in ignorance and error. But he understood enough of the word of God to know that many of the doc trines of the Romish church could not be found there. And he preached so many of the true doc trines of the Bible as well to entitle him to the hon orable name, The Morning Star of the Refor mation.

The "good parson'' was much beloved in his own parish; and many came from the villages around to his church, that they might hear the gospel from his lips.* He was often seen, with a portion of his * The carved oak pulpit in which he preached, the table on which he wrote, the chair in which he died, and the velvet robe, nearly de- stroyed by time, which he wore, are still preserved in the vestry of Lutterworth church.

[31] LUTTERWORTH CHURCH. written Bible under his arm, and staff in hand, visiting from house to house. The mansions of the gentry, the dwellings of the farmers, and the cot- tages of the field-laborers, were favored alike with his pastoral visits. He was the friend of all; he was ready to teach and comfort and pray for all at all times. Thus he lived, seeking the good of souls, his enemies opposing him even to the end of his days, though God did not permit them to cast him into prison, nor to bring him to a cruel death, as they desired. Continued labor at length broke down his health.

[32] One day, when in ehurcli, he was seized with a fatal attack of disease, and sunk to the ground. He was carried into his house, where he lay in a speech less state for two days, and then died. But though he was removed, he left behind him many disciples, who carried on the good work which he had so well begun.

Though Wycliffe never left his own land, to preach the truth across the seas, it was carried into almost every country of Europe by his writings.

His tracts and sermons were read by many awaken ed minds, and were the means of preparing them for a full knowledge of the gospel.

As his enemies could not prevail against him while he lived, they showed their hatred of his name and doctrine after his death. When his re- mains had lain in the grave for forty one years, they were dug up and burned, and the ashes cast into the little river Swift, which flows near the town where he labored. Thence, as an old writer says, they passed into the great river Severn, then in their onward course into the narrow seas, and at last into the wide ocean ; and thus became the em blem of the truth, which should flow from the little country town over England and the world. That it shall extend from the river to the ends of the earth," we know, for the word of God declares it. In this simple tale we see through what struggles and dangers some have passed for the gospeFs sake.

[33] The practical lesson we are taught is, to be at all times decided for the truth. By being decided, we do not mean to be noisy, or forward, or stubborn. One of the fruits of the Spirit is gentleness, which consists with the greatest firmness and decision in that which is right. We must in meekness instruct those that oppose the word of Grod. 2 Tim. ii. 25. Whilst we are valiant for the truth upon the earth," we are to speak that truth in love. Jer. ix. 3 ; Eph. iv. 15. Be decided, then, for God's word in opposition to all error. Let us be thankful for those whom God has raised up as examples of holy decision. They labored, and we enjoy the benefit of their labors. They planted a little sapling which took root, and has become a great tree, under whose boughs we now sit in peace. It was through God's grace working in them that we now possess a free and full Bible. Let us, then, give heed to the truths it contains, and yield our hearts to the gracious Saviour it makes known.

4

THE BOHEMIAN WITNESS

In the country that once formed the kingdom of Bohemia is a wide district known as the Black For est. Its northern parts consist of lofty mountains, whose rough ridges and peaks tower aloft to the height of five thousand feet. Some of these moun tain tops are bleak and barren, and during a great part of the year are covered with snow, which re flects a variety of colors as the frequent changes of light and shade of the sky pass over them. Others are covered with thick woods and forests of pine trees, presenting a bold, wild, and beautiful scene to the eye of the traveller. Ruins of castles, the homes of the nobles of former ages, still stand on many of these heights. In the southern portion of this range, the forest has been long since cleared by the hand of man. On their lovely slopes are pasture grounds and corn fields, orchards and vineyards, with cultivated farms here and there. Rivulets and lakes formed by the waters which flow from the mountains re- fresh the cultivated parts below.

It is now more than four hundred years since a [35] people sought a refuge in the caves and solitudes of the Black Forest. They were the Waldenses, of whom we heard in a former story. Among these disciples of Christ the devoted Peter Waldo found a home and a grave. And it was in one of their humble villages that John Huss, the Bohemian wit- ness for the truthJ was born. As a witness he bore testimony to the truth at the expense of his life. His history is full of interest. Let us dwell upon it for a short time. John Huss was the son of poor parents, who managed to send him to a public school. As they could not afford to pay any money, the boy acted as servant to one of the masters, who in return kindly lent him books, and helped to advance him in his learning. He was a diligent student, and as he grew up he rose from one step to another, till at length, when only twenty-four years of age, he was made the professor of divinity in the college of Prague. This was a high post for so young a man. At this time he was a Papist : but a nobleman placed in his hands some of the writings of Wycliffe, and advised him to read them. At first he thought them bold and full of danger ; but the more he studied them, the more he saw that they agreed with the word of God. They led him to the Scriptures, where he found many things different from the teachings of the church of Rome.

One day the archbishop of Prague ordered all the [36] writings of Wjcliffe that could be found in the dis trict of the Black Forest to be collected, and burn ed in the court of his palace. This was done amidst the mockery and songs of the people, who knew that the archbishop was an ignorant man, and sought to burn what he could not refute. In one of their songs they thus derided him : " He to the fire their books consigns, Of which he cannot read two lines," Huss spoke openly against the conduct of the arch- bishop, which led the priests to accuse him to the pope. A summons came for him to appear at Rome; but knowing that he could not safely go in person, he sent a friend thither to defend him. The latter was cast into prison, while Huss was declared to be a heretic. The pope, also, put every place in which he might dwell under an interdict or a curse. But Huss was not to be easily silenced, and he went on to spread the doctrines he had learned from Wycliffe, adding, however, as such witnesses for the truth always have done, that he was ready to give up his opinions if it could be proved from the Scriptures that he was in error. It was in the year 1412 that he made his boldest attack. The sellers of papal indulgences came to the city of Prague. They undertook to sell pardons of sin for money—a shocking delusion, which Huss exposed with great courage. On hearing of his op position, the pope ordered all public worship to [37] cease so long as the Reformer continued in the city of Prague.

Huss now judged it best to leave the place. But he could not refrain from witnessing against the evils of the times ; and, shut out from the city, ho preached in towns and villages, in the fields, and in the forest, and with such power and success, that, as it commonly happens in such cases, the rage of his enemies helped to the spread of the gospel.

The disorders in the church of Rome grew worse. There were three persons who strove for the office of pope. The three claimed to be infallible ; each asserted that he could not in any case act wrongly, and at the same time he cursed his rivals. Indeed, the whole church was like a diseased body. The words of the prophet could truly be applied to it ; "The whole head is sick, and the whole heart faint. From the sole of the foot even unto the head there is no soundness in it ; but wounds, and bruises, and putrifying sores : they have not been closed, neither bound up, nor mollified with ointment., , Isaiah i. 5, 6. It was now acknowledged by all parties that something must be done to put an end to such a disgraceful state of afi'airs. Accordingly, in 1414, a council was summoned by the emperor to meet at Constance As the day of meeting drew nigh, there had assembled one of the popes, Sigis mund emperor of G-ermany, thirty-four cardinals, 4* [38] twenty archbishops, one hundred and sixty bishops, two hundred and fifty abbots, four princes, twenty dukes, eighty counts, and more than seven hundred knights and other persons of rank. They had come from almost every known country in the world, and were persons of the greatest note in their age. At the opening of this famous council it was soon found that the pope and emperor were rivals to each other. The Bible teaches us to love one another ; and that ,Hhe fruit of the Spirit is love, joy, peace, long-sufiFering, gentleness, and meekness.,' But between these two great ones of the earth there was a deadly hatred. The emperor was crafty and de ceitful, and the pope was known to be one of the most openly wicked men of his times. Such were the leaders who were to settle the affairs of the church and the world !

Before this council John Huss was called to ap pear. He well knew the power of his enemies, and that when once in their hands they would not allow him to escape. He therefore did not obey the summons until the emperor gave him a mfv conduct that is, a written promise, which was to be a pledge that he should go and return without injury. We shall see how this promise was kept.

When Huss took leave of his friends, before he departed on his journey, he thus spoke to them: You know that I have taught you no error : con tinue in the truth, and trust in the mercy of God.

[39] Beware of false teachers. I am going to this great assembly, where the Lord will give me grace to en- dure trials, imprisonment, and, if it be his will, even the most dreadful death. Whatever happens, our joy will be great when we meet in the everlasting mansions/, As he went up to the council, the people of the towns and villages through which he passed came in crowds to meet him ; and in every place a loving welcome was given to him.

When he arrived at Constance, he sent a message to the pope that he was ready to meet all charges laid against him, saying, that as he had received a mfe conduct from the emperor, he hoped the head of the church would also grant him his protection.

The answer to this request was soon given ; he was seized, and cast into a dark and filthy dungeon by the side of a river, under the wicked pretence that no faith was to be kept with heretics.,' After he had been examined by the council, he was removed to a castle, where, in the day-time he was secured with chains in the vaults of his prison house ; and at night was fastened by a padlock to a wall. In this sad state he lay for six months.

Huss was not unprepared for this persecution ; he had made up his mind to suffer for Christ's sake. But in the midst of all his trouble and bondage he found light and comfort from the presence of his Saviour. His accusers tried to raise an uproar, and poured upon him every kind of reproach. They [40] said that he should be burned if he did not yield to the popOj and renounce the doctrines.he had preach ed. His only answer was, " Grod will not permit me to deny his truth/, After some time had passed, John Huss, on his forty-third birthday, stood once more before the council, which had now been sitting for many months. The emperor had come in great state, with his crown on his head, and his sceptre carried before him. Around him stood his princes and nobles. The cardinals, bishops, and others, too, were there to pronounce the sentence of death on the poor [41] prisoner. They placed him on a high stage or plat form, that he might be seen by the whole assembly, and a band of soldiers stood around him. The good man felt his position to be one of great peril ; and though there was no one to stand up for his cause, he knew that his God and Saviour was nigh to hear and help him. Falling on his knees, he prayed for grace that he might be faithful to the end. After his enemies had accused him of heresy, sentence was passed upon him that he should be publicly burned. His only answer was a prayer. 0 Lord God/, he cried, " I beseech thee, for thy mercy's sake, to pardon all my enemies ; for thou knowest that I have been falsely accused, and unjustly con- demned. But do thou forgive them this sin.'', Again his enemies loudly accused him, calling him by the name of Judas, and in other ways casting reproach upon him. To which he meekly replied, I place all my confidence and hope in God my Saviour. I know he will never take from me the cup of salvation, but that by his grace I shall drink it to-day in his kingdom.,' The hearts of these nobles and clergy were closed against all pity for their helpless prisoner. They derided him, placing on his head a paper crown, about two feet high, on which were painted three devils, and in large letters the word, Arch-heretic.,' On seeing it, Huss calmly said, My Lord Jesus bore for me, a poor sinner, a painful crown of thorns.

[42] and died the shameful death of the cross. There fore, for his sake, I will cheerfully bear this lighter crown. "Now we deliver up your soul to Satan, and to hell/, cried the bishops. But I/, added Huss, commit my soul to my gracious Lord, Jesus Christ." In this manner he was, without any delay, led out to the place of execution, in a meadow in the midst of the gardens outside of the city. Eight hundred soldiers guarded him : a mighty host, in- deed, to take charge of a poor unarmed man ! The crowd of people was so great, that they were obliged to shut the gates of the city, and only to let them out by companies, lest the bridge over which they passed should break down under them.

The behavior of Huss, on his way to the place of his death, was calm and even joyful. As he passed the archbishop's palace, seeing his enemies burning his books in the great square, he smiled at their vain display of malice. On going a little further, he cried out, 0 Jesus Christ, Son of the living God, have pity upon me;" and he continued to utter similar petitions till he came to the place of execution. The people who listened to him said, " We know not what this man has taught and preached before, but we hear nothing from him now but holy words and Christian prayers.', When he arrived at the spot where he must die, he fell on his knees, lifting up his eyes to heaven, [43] and praying aloud, in language taken from the 31st and 51st Psalms, repeating very solemnly this verse : Into thine hand I commit my spirit : thou hast redeemed me, 0 Lord God of truth/, After a brief pause Huss begun to pray again : "Lord Jesus, I cheerfully suffer this terrible and cruel death, for the sake of thy holy gospel, and the preaching of thy sacred word : do thou forgive my enemies the crime they are committing/, On this the execu tioners made him cease, and compelled him to walk three times rt)und the pile of wood. He then asked that he might speak to his jailers : and when they were come, he said, "I thank you most sincerely for all the kindness you have shown me, for you have behaved to me more as brethren than as keepers.

Know, also, that my trust in my Saviour is un shaken, for whose sake I willingly suffer this death, being assured I shall be with him this day in Paradise. The executioners then took him, and bound him to a stake with wet ropes. They fixed round his neck a black rusty chain, on which he said, smiling.

My dear Master and Saviour was bound for my sake with a harder and heavier chain than this. Why should I, a poor sinful man, be ashamed of thus being bound for his sake?" The wood was put in order, and some bundles of light furze were placed under his feet, with heaps of straw and large wood around him up to his neck. The pile was then [44] lighted, and the flames began to wrap round the body of the martyr. At that moment, the voice of singing was heard. It was poor Huss in the midst of his pains praising Grod. Then several times the cry came from the midst of the fire, " 0 Christ, Son of Grod, have mercy on me." But the wind soon drove the flames into his face, and stopped his voice; still, however, his head and his lips were seen to move, as if in prayer, for a short time, when the Lord ended the sufierings of his faithful servant ; his body fell into the flames, life was gone, and his soul entered on its eternal rest. The ashes of Huss were put into a cart, with the earth on which he had been executed, and the whole thrown into the Rhine, which flowed near, that not a trace of this holy witness for the truth might be left. But, as an elegy composed at this time says ; His ashes will be scattered over every country : no river, no banks will be able to retain them ) and those whom the enemy thought to silence by death, thus sing and publish, in every place, that gospel, which his persecutors thought to suppress. Whilst we shudder at the wickedness of men, as we read this account, let us ever keep in mind that God, who is infinite in wisdom, overlooks and con trols all events. He guides and directs with an un seen hand all human afiairs, and makes all things fulfil his gracious purpose. Out of persecutions [45] and trials he has ever made good to come. The lighting the fires of the martyrs was one of the means of dispersing the darkness of the middle ages y and the courage of these servants of God in the midst of suffering, led the people to inquire after the truth of those principles for which they died.

THE MONK THAT SHOOK THE WORLD.

In the year 1497 two boys were seen passing through a small city in Germany. They walked slowly, and at times stopped before the doors of the houses, and sung carols about the infant Jesus. It was Christmas time, and the weather was cold and frosty. The evening was drawing on ; and the bright glare of the fires within the houses of that old city of Eisenach shone forth through the small windows on the hoar frost without. These poor lads belonged to a school kept by some monks, who gave their pupils quite as many blows and angry words as lessons of learning. As was the custom of the times, they had been sent to beg their bread from street to street, singing as they went along. The better to move the heart to charity they sang of Him whose lowly birth was at that seasoii of the year called to mind.

That day these minstrel boys had met with only frowns and repulses ; and they thought of returning, cold and hungry as they were to their home. But there was the house of Conrad Cotta nigh at hand. He was the burgomaster, or chief magistrate, of the [47] city : perhaps, if they sang before his door they might get some help, for his wife Ursula was well known for deeds of kindness. It was their last hope, and so they sang their carol in their sweetest style. Ursula was very fond of music; and, hearing the sounds, she stood at the window till the song was finished. The singing of one boy was more musical than the other. It was the voice of young Martin Luther which fixed her attention. She had often listened to it with delight before in the great church of the city, and now, as she gazed on his pale, intelligent face, she felt the deepest pity. A gentle, loving heart had Ursula Cotta. She had seen the boys driven from three doors, but there awaited them kind words and charity at her dwell ing. When the carol was ended, she made signs for them to approach. It was not often that they were spoken to in such a gentle manner; and when she asked Martin from whence he came, and what was his father's name, how great was her delight to find that he was a kinsman of her husband !

The boys were soon placed before a cheerful fire ; and after a good supper they were ready to sing to good Ursula their most favorite carol. When that was ended, young Martin sang the forty-sixth Psalm. From that day, Martin became a frequent visitor at her house. She was as a second mother to him; and often did he seek to repay her kindness [48] by one of his sweetest songs, or by a few strains on his flute. Five years had passed away, and Martin had be- come a student in a college. He had met with many kind friends ; and his father too (who had been a poor woodcutter) by this time was able to assist him with money. This was a great comfort to the young man ; he could now pursue his studies with better hope of success. In the college there was a large room, where he spent every moment he could spare. This room was the library, from the shelves of which he took down book after book, and read them with profit and delight. But there was one large heavy volume he had never yet opened.

At length he took it from its place, and found it was a Bible printed in the Latin language. He was now nearly twenty years of age, and had been brought up almost all his life in schools and colleges, and this was the first time he had met with the Holy Scriptures. It is true, he had been told there was a book called the Bible, but he had never seen a copy of it. With feelings of surprise and interest he turned over the leaves. He had not expected to findr it so large a volume ; and there were writers in it whose names or works he had never heard of. Beginning at the first page, he read on till he came to the history of Hannah and the child-prophet Samuel. It was to him all new and beautiful, and full of instruction. As he left the library that night, [49] he said to himself, Oh that God would give me such a book for my own V' That old Bible became to him more precious than gold, and sweeter than honey to his taste. He turned over its pages with constant pleasure, as often as he could run into the library for a few hours. Little did he then think that his hands would give that holy volume, trans- lated by himself into German, to millions of his countrymen, and to be a blessing for hundreds of years after he was laid in the grave. Three more years passed, and Martin Luther be- came a monk in another convent. The Bible he had read in the college library had aroused serious thoughts in his mind ; but like the Ethiopian trea- surer, in the eighth chapter of the Acts, he needed that " some man should guide', him to understand the Scriptures. He was looking to his prayers and fastings as the sure way of gaining heaven. He saw not that a sinner can only be saved through faith in Christ Jesus. He knew not clearly of the love of God. Every time he heard his holy name, he was pale with terror. The knowledge of God in Christ reconciling the world unto himself, and of the grace of the Saviour, were to him hidden truths. His trust was more in saints and angels, in human merits and tears of penitence, than in the glorious work of the one Mediator. The monks with whom Martin lived were more ignorant than himself; he could not therefore be 5* [50] taught by them ; besides, they cared more about his doing the work of a servant, that they might live at ease. They made him attend the gates, sweep the church, and clean the rooms. And, as soon as the young monk had fiijished this labor, they would say to him, " Go with your bag through the town that is, in search of food for the convent. When they found him at his books, they cried aloud, Come, come; it is not by study, but by begging corn, eggs, fish, and money, that you benefit the cloister.', Poor Martin found that by entering a convent he had changed his garments, but not his heart. He found no peace there. " Oh,,' he said, what will deliver me from my sins, and make me holy ! How shall I satisfy the justice of God ? How shall I appear before him He almost pined away from sorrow of heart. God was thus trying him with small trials that he might the better here after bear great ones. After Martin had been some time in this convent he again met with a copy of that precious book which formerly so astonished and delighted him when a student, but it was chained. He could, not take it to his sleeping cell to read, nor remove it from its place, so he sat by it every time he could secretly get to the room where it was fixed. Some times he learned by heart long passages from that chained Bible, to repeat to himself when in his cell at night. The more he read, the more light came [51] into his mind. He began to see the evil of sin, the wickedness of his own heart, and more than all, the rich grace and love of Jesus. He also began to detect the follies and corruptions of the church of Rome.

Two events, at this time, led his mind in the further search after the truth. x\s he sat in the company of some friends, one of them was suddenly killed. He then said to himself, What would be- [52] come of me, if I were thus suddenly called away?', On his return from a visit to his father, the clouds covered the sky with blackness, and a violent thunderstorm broke over his head. As he hastened along the road to find a shelter, the lightning struck the ground near to his feet. He was startled and alarmed, but was unhurt. Stopping on his journey, he fell on his knees, and prayed to God to save him. When he arose, he said, I must be- come holy.'' But he knew not of the work of the Holy Spirit on the heart, leading to a life of faith and holiness. Whatever Martin Luther did to find peace was still in vain. Those who saw his conduct said he was a devout man ; but he replied, " I am a great sinner : how is it possible for me to satisfy Divine justice?'' Salvation could not be in himself; " how then," he thought, " can I obtain it !" But the light of day was now dawning on the darkness of his mind. The Holy Spirit was convincing him of sin, and bringing him to feel his need of a Saviour. About this time there came to the convent an old man named Staupitz. He saw how ill the poor young man looked ; and he asked, " Why are you so sad, brother Martin ?" " Ah," said Luther, " I do not know what will become of me; it is in vain I make promises to God —sin is ever the strongest." Oh, my friend," said Staupitz, calhng to mind [53] how he had felt, instead of torturing yourself on account of your sins, cast yourself by faith into the Reedemer's arms—look at the wounds of Jesus Christ,—to the blood that he has shed for you. God is not angry with you, it is you who are angry with God. Listen to the Son of God; he became man to give you the promise of Divine favor. By his stripes are you healed ; by his blood are your sins cleansed away. Love him who first loved you; and in order that you may be filled with the love of what is good, you must first be filled with love for God." What good words—what light and peace did they afi'ord ! Luther listened for his life. There was one part of the Bible he now studied with great diligence and interest. It was the Epistle of Paul to the Romans. A nd in that he saw clearly the way in which God could be just and the justi fier of the ungodly. From that time he found peace in believing." Then he was filled with love, and sought to obey God, not from fear, nor with the hope of getting to heaven through his own merits, but from the love which he felt as a child of God to his heavenly Father. Years rolled on, and Luther became a preacher, the head of a college, and a doctor of divinity. As his influence became great, and still more great, he made known to others the truths he had found so precious to his own soul. He boldly exposed the vain teachings of the priests, their craft and evil [54] conduct. The fame of his labors soon spread in the land, and many came to hear the gospel from his lips. In the churches, the college halls, and the open air, he set forth the only way in which a sin- ner can be saved. In one of his preaching tours, Luther came to a city in which his early friends Conrad and Ursula Cotta had found a home. They had by this time lost nearly all their property ; the once rich burgo- master was now a poor man, and the troubles of life had filled his heart with sorrow. He had been told that a great preacher was on his way to the city. They tell me," said Conrad to his wife, " that he talks bravely of free grace—that pardon for sin is to be had without money and without price. " That would just do for us,', replied Ursula; "et us go to the church and hear him.'' The old church that day was well filled, for nobles and merchants, working men and maidens, had come to listen to the bold preacher. Among them sat Conrad and Ursula. Strange thoughts and feelings must have moved them as they listened to the powerful voice of the monk. But when they heard him give out a psalm to be sung—his favor ite forty-sixth psalm — " God is our refuge," they called to mind that Christmas evening when the minstrel boy of Eisenach sang it by their own fireside.

[55] The words that were preached sank deep into the heart of Ursula, and from that hour she was brought to know the only way in which she could be saved. Nor was this all ; for Martin Luther was now in a condition to show his gratitude, and repay the kind ness of those who, in the days of his youth, took in to their house a poor friendless boy.

The time at last came when Luther was called forth openly to enter on the blessed Reformation.

The occasion was the opening of a great market by the church of Rome. Crowds of anxious buy ers : men and women, rich and poor, old and young, flocked there to spend their money. The dealers were monks, who smiled and joked as they offered to sell their goods at the cheapest rate. But what was it they had to sell ? It was, they said, the sal- vation of the soul! These dealers passed through the country in a gay carriage; three horsemen rode by their side, and servants went before them to make known their approach. As they came near to a town, the magistrates, priests, nuns, and the trades, went forth to welcome them with music, flags, and lighted tapers, amidst the ringing of bells and the shoutings of the people. We may suppose we see them as they reach the market-place. The three monks seat themselves at a table, and raise a red flag, having on it the pope,s coat of arms. Be fore them is a money-chest ; and now one of them named Tetzel, begins the sale. Come near," he [56] cries aloud, and I will give you indulgences—let- ters duly sealed, by wliich even the sins you here after commit shall be all forgiven you : even repent- ance is not necessary. But more than this; these letters will not only save the living, but also the dead. The very moment the money chinks against the bottom of the chest, the soul escapes from pur gatory, * and flies to heaven. Bring your money ; bring money; bring money/,f The whole account of this shameful and wicked imposture is almost too shocking for belief. There was one whose spirit was roused, and who preached and wrote against Tetzel and his traffic. It was Martin Luther, the monk, who was now pre- pared for the contest which he saw before him.

Though he almost stood alone, he resolved, with God's help, to witness to the truth and expose false- hood. He more than ever attacked the errors of the church of Rome. And what v/as better still, he clearly and boldly declared the two great Protestant doctrines—that the Bible, the whole Bible, and nothing but the Bible, is the rule of our faith ; and that a man can be justified—pardoned and accepted of Grod—only by believing in and trusting in the * Purgatory is said by Roman Catholics to be a place of punishment, where souls are purged, or cleansed by fire, from sin. But this is a vain and wicked deceit : Scripture does not teach us anything about such a place : it tells us that " the blood of Jesus Christ cleanseth," or purgeth, " from all sin ;" and this is enough ; there is no need of a purgatory. fMerle d'Aubigne's History of the Reformation [57] atonement and righteousness of our Lord Jesus Christ. His success among the people filled his enemies with rage. Tetzel sought to frighten the people by ordering a large fire to be lighted in the principal square of the city, declaring that he had orders from the pope to imprison or burn all those who dared to op- pose the sale of indulgences. Only wait," said the priests, a fortnight, or at most a month, and that heretic, Luther, will be burned alive.'' But God did not let him fall into their power. The preaching of Luther soon found favor with princes, nobles, learned doctors, and students, as well as large numbers of the common people. As the priests could not put him down, the pope wrote against him "2i bull', —or a decree by which he was given over to persecution in this world and eternal death in the next. Ofi&cers were sent to burn his writings, and to publish the bull in the town where Luther lived. But the reformer was not less bold than the pope. Placing himself at the head of a crowd of doctors, students, and friends, he went to the market-place. A fire was lighted, and, as the flames arose, he cast into them a copy of the laws of the Romish church, and the pope's bull. The spectators were filled with joy, for they had long felt the harsh and cruel power of these laws. When all was burned to ashes, Luther quietly walked to his home. By this act he made known to 6 [58] the world that he had for ever separated from the pope.

LUTHER BURNING THE POPE'S BULL. Luther was now summoned to appear before a diet, an assembly of princes, nobles, cardinals and bishops, in the city of Worms, to answer all charges that might be brought against him. "Do not go,,' said his friends ; your enemies will seize your person, and cast you into prison. " Christ liveth,', replied Luther; "and I will go to Worms, in spite of all the powers of darkness. Besides, a safe conduct is provided me.'' But,'' urged his friends, was not a royal letter, with a promise of safe conduct [59] given to John Huss, and yet he was betrayed and burned/, Luther then concluded the debate by saying, ',1 must make a confession of the truth be fore the diet. I will go, trusting in Christ. I am bound to stand up in defence of his gospel.', And he went, and before the princes and priests made a bold and brave confession of the truth. Finding they could not prevail, they commanded him to depart at once from the town ; but his friends learned that there was a plot laid to arrest him on the road, though a safe conduct had been given to him. Luther obeyed, and went forth; but as he came near to a forest, five armed men suddenly opened the door of the carriage in which he rode, pulled him out, placed him on a horse, and riding through the forest, came at length to the castle of Wartburg. But this was a friendly capture. It was a plan to save him from the craft and cruelty of his ever-watchful foes. In the castle of Wart- 'burg, which he called his Patmos—his place of ex ile—he lived for ten months. He, however, though alone, was not idle here. He spent his time in writing books and tracts, and translating the New Testament into German.

Once more Luther came forth to carry on the work of God in public ; and in spite of the rage of his enemies, and the threats of the pope, the empe ror, and the diet, he openly exposed the errors of the church of Rome and called on all men to come [60] CASTLE OF WARTBURG.

out from her, that they might not partake of her sins.The writings of Luther were now spread far and wide. Three presses were fully at work in printing them. His books passed from hand to hand ; they were carried into quiet valleys, and over some of the [61] highest mountains. They were read in the palaces of princes, in places of learning, and in the homes of the poor. Ships carried them over wide seas, and they were reprinted in Switzerland, France, Eng land, and other lands, until thousands of people were made to rejoice in the good news of salvation.

It is said that within the space of little more than four years after publication a traveller purchased some of his works in the far-distant city of Jerusalem ! Even little children shared his love and labors. For them he wrote many sweet little hymns, which are still sung, like the Divine Songs of the good Dr. Watts, in our land, by thousands of the young in Germany. Popery then received a check which it has never recovered, and a wound from the sword of God's word of which it must die. Who can tell the full results of the labors of that bold and ear- nest man — ** The solitary monk that shook the world From Pagan slumber, when the gospel trump, Thundered its challenge from a dauntless lip In peals of truth ?" There is a lesson, among many others, we may learn from the history of Luther. It is, that we may have much religious knowledge, and yet not know Christ as the Saviour of sinners. Even those in our days who have had the Bible from their ear liest youth, may yet be strangers to its blessed truths. 6* [62] They may "go about to establish their own right eousness thinking that they can become entitled to heaven by their own worthiness. They understand not the great doctrine which Luther after a long struggle was led to receive, and which is revealed in the word of Grod : Salvation—Salvation by Christ—and Salvation by Christ alone ; for, Neither is there salvation in any other : for there is none other name under heaven given among men, whereby we must be saved." Acts iv. 12.

Have you, dear young reader, felt the evil and burden of sin ? Do you look by faith to Jesus Christ that you may be saved ? Are you willing to profess his name, and labor in his cause, even though you may suffer reproach and shame for his sake ? Happy are they who in the morning of their days yield their hearts to the truth as it is in Jesus.* * An original Life of Luther, written by the Rev. Dr. Sears for the American Sunday-school Union, will be found one of the most inter- esting and instructive volumes extant. It is enriched by a large number of beautiful engravings, and the initial letter of each chapter, and indeed all the pictorial embellishments are illustrative of some subject connected with the biography. The work was republished by the Religious Tract Society of London.

THE YOUTHFUL MARTYR

In the days of the young king, Edward the Sixth, a Bible was placed on a desk in every church of the land, for the use of the people. A copy in large print, bound in wooden boards, with curious iron clasps, was then seen fastened by a chain to a strong upright stand. As " the word of God was precious in those days''—for it was costly and scarce, and many truly loved it—those who had a small share of learning read it aloud to those who had less abil- ity than themselves. Thus light began to spread, when a dark cloud came over this hopeful state of things; for queen Mary, astern papist, ascended the throne of England, and quickly ordered the removal of the Bibles. In a few places, however, her com- mands were either not received or were not obeyed.

Whatever was the cause, it is certain that there still lay the old Bible on a stand just inside the porch of the little chapelry at Brentwood, in Essex, England.

It was in the spring of the year 1555, that a youth, named William Hunter, entered the church to read the book he loved. He was an apprentice [64] to a London weaver, but was now on a visit to his native town. The lad was one of those who were faithful to the truth, and who would rather suffer for it, than sin against it. As he stood reading the holy book, and lifting up his heart in prayer, a man of the name of Atwell, a summoner or officer of the popish bishop, came that way, and saw him so engaged. " Why meddlest thou with the Bible V said the officer, not a little angry that a boy should dare to open the Book of God. Knowest thou how to read ? And canst thou expound the Scriptures The youth modestly replied, Father Atwell, I take not upon me to expound the Scriptures; but finding the Bible here, I read it for my comfort.,' The officer then began to speak scornfully of the sacred word as a hurtful book. Say not so,,' said William, in a kind and re- spectful manner, "it is God's book, out of which every one that hath grace may learn to know what pleaseth God, and what is displeasing to him.', Could we not tell formerly,' ' inquired Atwell, as well as now, how God was to be served Not so well as now,'' added William, "if we might have his blessed word among us still, as we have had ; and I pray God that we may have the blessed Bible among us continually." As Atwell could not prevail with the lad, he cried, "I see you are one who dislikes the queen's [65] laws. I have heard how you* left London on that account ; but if you do not turn, you, as well as many other heretics, will broil for your opinions. " God give me grace," meekly replied William, that I may believe his word, and confess his name, whatever may come of it." Confess his name shouted old AtwelL "No, no, you will go to the devil, all of you.,' Atwell quickly left the chapel, and meeting a priest, returned with him to where William was reading, when the priest began to upbraid and threaten him. The youth well knew what this meant, so he hastened to his father's house, and taking a hasty leave of his parents fled from the town. It was a sad time when the young who loved the Lord had to leave the homes of their early days, and seek their dwelling and food wherever they could find them.

A few days after William had gone, a justice sent for the father, and ordered him to produce his son. "What, sir,'' said the parent, would you have me seek my son, that he may be burned The justice was resolute ; and upon this errand the poor father was obliged to depart. He rode about for two or three days, hoping to satisfy the justice without finding his son. The lad, however, saw his father at a distance, and went to meet him. On learning the danger of his parent he said he would return, rather than place his father in any peril.

[66] And yet how could the aged parent secure his own safety by the surrender of his child? It was a struggle of affection : at length he yielded, and they went together into the town. When the evening drew on, William and his father ascended the hill that leads to the little town of Brentwood. The cottagers bade them good cheer as they passed them on their way ; but it was with heavy hearts and weeping eyes that they looked for- ward to the coming morrow. They had not, how ever, to wait till the morning dawn, for during the night the young Christian was seized, and hurried to the stocks. There he lay, till break of day, pained in body, but happy in mind.

Early in the morning, William was taken before a justice of the peace, who, after trying in vain to shake his faith, ordered him to be carried to the old palace in the fields of Bethnal Green—about sixteen miles away—where Bonner, the popish bishop of London, then resided. When he stood in the hall of the palace, the bishop first spoke to him gently, then sternly, and then roughly ; but still the youth would not promise to give up the Bible, and deny its truths. " Away with him again to the stocks,, , cried the bishop, and to the stocks William was again hurried. Two long days and nights he there lay, without any food, except a crust of brown bread and a small supply of water. Poor boy, what were his thoughts in these hours of trial ? Alone, [67] oppressed, and with the prospect of a painful death before him, what did he suffer? What were the prayers and cries which then went up to God from his heart ? Surely he had grace given to him to bear all with humble trust and patience ; or, like Paul and Silas, as he felt the pressure of the wood on his legs, he may have sung praises unto God. We can- not but believe that his Saviour, who tenderly feels for his suffering disciples, gave to him to taste his choicest comfort and love. Not satisfied with this act of cruelty, his enemies proceeded to further lengths, in the hope of sub- duing his spirit. The bishop sent illiam to one of the London prisons, with strict orders to the jailer to put as many iron chains upon him as he could possibly bear. And in a dungeon he was confined for three-quarters of a year, hoping, trust- ing, praying always.

Bishop Bonner one day thought of the Bible- loving lad in prison, and hoping that his long con- finement, together with the natural love of liberty and home, had made him more ready to yield, sent for him to his palace. But the spirit of the young martyr was yet unbroken, and his trust in the gos pel as firm as before. "If you recant,', said the bishop, "I will give you forty pounds, and set you up in business. This was a large sum of money in those days, and the offer was very tempting, but it was at once rejected.

[68] "I will make you steward of my own house," added Bonner, in a gentle and crafty manner.

"But, my lord," was the reply, "If you cannot persuade my conscience by Scripture, I cannot find in my heart to turn from God for the love of the world ; for I count all worldly things but loss, in comparison with the love of Christ." Will neither threats nor promises avail ? Then away with him to the fire. When William again entered his native town, he knew it was to endure a painful death. But yet he knew what his Saviour had suffered for him. And he remembered, too, the words, " Be thou faithful unto death, and I will give thee a crown of life.'' There was no prison in the little town, so the mar tyr youth was confined in an inn, and guarded by constables. His mother heard of his return, and with true love rushed to the place where he lay. Charity moved the hearts of the guards, and they allowed her to see him, and to sit by his side. And when she found him happy and constant, she bless- ed God for such a son, and the more so when he said: "For my little pain which I shall sufi'er, Christ hath procured for me a crown of joy ; are you not glad of that, mother ?" They then knelt down and she prayed to God to strengthen her poor boy to the end. At length the morning came that young William was to die. The sherifi", justices, and priests were duly in attendance, with executioners and guards, [69] while a crowd of people had come together, to the last sad scene. As the young martyr was led along from the inn, his father rushed forward towards him in an agony of parental feeling. Throwing his arms around the neck of his noble son, he said, with flowing tears, God be with thee, son William.,' The son calmly looked for the last time on his dear parent, and replied, God be with you, father; THE YOUTHFUL MARTYR. be of good comfort; I trust we shall meet again where we shall rejoice together.

There were many weeping eyes on that day in 7 [70] the little town of Brentwood. To see one so young —a kind, gentle, pious lad—dragged through the streets to bear the scorching flames, whose only offence was that he loved the gospel, was a sight that touched the hardest heart, and brought tears on many a manly cheek. William, as he passed along, saw his father's cottage, and cast a last look on his sorrowing sisters. He bade farewell to those who had been the playmates and friends of his ear liest days. He was now to suffer in the cause of Christ, and they saw that he feared not to die. At last, the procession came to the end of the town, where the stake and chain and fagots were ready.

Without loss of time he was secured by the chain, and wood was piled around. While this was being done, a pardon was offered if he would profess him self a papist.

"No,'' said William, resolutely, "I will not re- cant, God willing. Then turning to the people he asked them to pray for him. " Pray for thee cried a hard-hearted justice who was looking on, I will no more pray for thee than I would for a dog.'' "I pray Grod this may not be laid to your charge at the last day," was William's calm reply.

A priest, too, began to taunt him ; until a gentle- man spoke aloud, May God have mercy on his soul;" and the people mournfully added, Amen." The fire was now lighted, and as the flames began [71] to rise, William, who still held in his hand a book of Psalms, threw it into the hands of his brother, who had followed him to the place of death. His brother calling to him said, William, think on the sufferings of Christ, and be not afraid." "I am not afraid,'' added the martyr. "Lord, Lord, receive my spirit." These were his last words. The fire was lighted; the dry fagots burned briskly; and the flames soon wrapped around his body. In a few minutes his sufferings were at an end for ever.

THE martyr's tree, BRENTWOOD. An old elm tree still marks the spot, near which William Hunter yielded up his life for the truth.

[72] Though three hundred years have passed since then, his name is not forgotten. His soul has joined the noble army of martyrs', in heaven ; but the record of his faith and courage will long survive on earth. Let us learn from his history:—1. The import- ance of early decision in the cause and service of Christ; as a preservative in times of error and false religion.

2. The need of constancy in resisting the most tempting offers to deny our Master. Like Moses the servant of God, let us choose rather to suffer aflSiction with the people of God, than to enjoy the pleasures of sin for a season; esteeming the re- proach of Christ greater riches than the treasures in Egypt.- 3. The blessing of having pious parents. The father and mother of William could give up such a son to Christ for Christ, encouraging him, even in the prospect of death, not to renounce the truth. May your parents never be called to such a test of love.

4. The true character of Popery. Can that be the pure and holy religion of Jesus—the religion of love and mercy—which commits such dreadful deeds ? Christ was kind and loving to all. He came "not % to destroy men,s lives, but to save them.- When his disciples would have used the sword, and have called " down fire from heaven,- he rebuked them.

How different from his gentle and merciful spirit has been the conduct of cruel persecutors in every age !

THE PROTESTANTS.

There have been Protestants from the first : those who have ,protested against the errors of the age. They have been mostly a "little flock," often driven into the caves of the mountains, or hidden in forests and sheltered valleys, yet have they not failed to bear a testimony for God and his truth. Among these pious worthies were the Waldenses. In very early times the glad news of redeeming love was carried to them, and it took deep root in their hearts. It met a welcome, and was believed, loved, and cherished. In their lowly valleys they long kept the faith," protected by their humble and obscure condition ; while the nations around them were sunk in the greatest errors. The range of mountains known as the Alps lies north of Italy and east of France. Towards the south side of this range is the country of Piedmont, and here, on a small tract of land, still live the "men of the valleys,,' the descendants of the early Waldenses, the " martyr people,,' as they were called—the Protestants of their times. Their homes sti,etch up the Alps, and down into [85] the plain below, and are formed into little hamlets and villages. Those by the plain are very pleasant, with meadows and vineyards, wheat and rye fields, and gardens. Mulberry trees fringe the road-sides, giving food for the vast multitudes of silkworms, which spin silk for the people to trade in. Higher up, the way winds among huge frowning cliffs, by the sides of which torrents dash down to the plains below. Here and there are little valleys open to the sun, edged by forests of firs, warm and green, where a cluster of cottages lie nestled close together, sur- rounded by patches of potatoes and corn, while herds of cattle and flocks of goats are grazing on the grassy spots of the mountain side. Still higher up, the trees dwindle to dwarfs ; deep snows cover the peaks, and masses of ice, which sometimes tumble down from the heights, destroying everything in their way. Here everything looks wild and dreary, and you wonder how any one can live there. In this diversified region of snow and sunshine, of peak and hollow, live the successors of the martyr people, numbering now, perhaps, about twenty-two thousand souls. Away up in their mountain retreats the Walden ses never fell into the same corrupt way of thinking of the gospel as nearly all the rest of Europe had. No ; they, to a great extent, held fast to the pure word of God, They said, Men ought not to go to Rome for the pardon of their sins, nor seek to 8* [86] saints and relics for help. "The church," they declared, " is founded, not on St. Peter, much less on the pope ; but upon Christ and his doctrines as taught in the Bible.'' They maintained that it was wicked idolatry to worship images, or so much as to have them in the churches. Behold, how they protested against Popery ! They were real Pro testants long before Luther's reformation, or before the name Protestant" was given to Christians. For several hundred years nobody thought of harming these lowly people in their mountain val leys. They had no riches to tempt the great and the warlike to invade their homes. It was almost as though they were forgotten by the rest of the world. And thus shielded from many of the evils which came upon others, they were in a great measure faithful to the truth as it is in Christ. As they grew in love to the Saviour, they wanted others to love him also, and to enjoy the light and comfort which he can give to the soul. So poor little Al- pine churches sent missionaries out, two by two, to France, to Germany, to Italy, and all about. Is it not beautiful to see how the love of Christ moves the heart ? It not only makes us desire to be good, but to do good. It leads us to deny ourselves, and seek to relieve the sorrows of others. That is just what Jesus did. He came into the world to seek and to save the lost. "He came not to be ministered unto, but to minister." He was as a servant for the [87] good of others. So will his true followers, when filled with his love, strive to benefit all on whom they can exert an influence. Not only did these children of the Alps send missionaries forth, but colporteurs, or book-hawkers also. Thus did they employ these agents more than four hundred years ago—pious pedlars, who, with their goods, carried leaves of the Bible, and icritten tracts—for this was before the invention of printing—and left them with those found willing to receive them. In ways like these, Bible piety was kept alive in many hearts and homes and hamlets, while the darkness of Popery rested on the nominally Christian world. These Waldenses, then, were among the first Pro testants in the church. But we will now pass to the time when the name Protestant was to be distinctly adopted by those who refused to submit to the church of Rome.

The case was similar to that of which we read in the New Testament, when all who were the follow ers of Jesus were Christians, before they were so called in the city of Antioch (Acts xi. 26 ;) but after that time they went forth glorying in the name of their Divine Master. So from the time of which we now speak men began to rejoice in the name of Protestants. Spire is an ancient city on the banks of the river Rhine, in Germany. In the days of Luther it was a place of great trade and wealth. Lofty towers [88] lined its strong walls ; noble buildings adorned its streets ; and pleasant walks were formed on the out side of the city. This place was selected by Charles the Fifth, the emperor of Germany, to hold a "diet', or assembly, to consult on the state of the country and of the Roman Catholic church. This emperor, his brother Ferdinand, (king of Spain,) and the pope, were the three great enemies of the Reforma tion. They were bold, rich, and powerful, and were CITY OF SPIRE. quite resolved to put an end to the "new doctrines,'' as they called them ; though, indeed, they were the old doctrines preached by the Apostles. In the [89] hope to stop their progress, they called this great assembly in this famous place of resort. Before the day came for the diet to commence business, the Roman Catholic princes and bishops entered the city of Spire with great pomp aod mili- tary array, as if they were going to war. One or two of the princes who favored the Reformation also drew nigh at the head of their horsemen; while others were attended with only a few learned and pious men, whose calm and cheerful looks showed that they were not ashamed of the cause they were about to plead. Besides these, there were deputies or persons acting on the part of several of the "free cities'' of Germany. Never before was there a great er gathering for such a purpose in any country of Europe.

The Protestant princes wore these letters braided on their right sleeves, v. D. M. i. being the first letters of the Latin words Verhum Domini manet in jEternum, (" The word of the Lord en- dureth for ever,'' 1 Peter i. 25.) The same letters were placed over the doors of the hotels in Spire where they lodged. Thus the Bible was the ensign under which they stood arrayed.

It had boen proposed that the princes of the German empire should be at liberty to make such reforms in their churches as they saw necessary, with the permission of the emperor. This the pope did not like at all. Liberty of conscience he strongly opposed. People must not think for [90] themselves in matters of religion," he said, "or make what reforms they please ; but they must think and act according to what the church of Rome teaches, and that church alone." They were resolved to put down all religious liberty. They first sent down an order that the gospel should not be preached in the city of Spire by the reformers ; but the princes, on their arrival, urged their right to a place of worship for their use. Their demand was sternly denied. The princes then ordered their preachers to conduct divine service in the halls of their palaces and hotels ; and such was the thirst of the people to hear the word, that eight thousand of them were present one Lord's day during the morning and evening worship of the evangelical princes. While the papal worship was carried on in the beautiful cathedral of Spire, before a small number of people, crowds from town and country filled the places where the word of God was preached by the reformed pastors. The princes thus boldly made known their faith. They said they would give up their kingdoms and their lives rather than submit to what they believed was wrong. We will,'' said they, obey the emperor in everything that may maintain peace and the honor of God; but we cannot submit to give up the truths of the Bible, nor the simple worship of God." The princes were out-voted by the diet, but not cast down. Let us reject the decrees which re- fuse us redress," they cried; in matters of con- [91] science we must endure everything, sacrifice every- thing—our crowns, our lives—rather than give up the word of God." But they soon found that the diet spurned their claims, and would not listen to their words. Had not, then, the time come for them to make a solemn protest against the false and shameful conduct of their opposers? Yes; they all saw it was the hour to make a brave stand for the truth ; and hand to hand, and heart to heart, they went forward in the course of duty.

THE PROTEST AT SPIRE. It was on the 25th of April, 1529, that they met in a little room on the ground floor of a minister's [92] house in St. John's Lane, in the city of Spire— a room which is still shown to the traveller. And there, with prayerful and brave hearts, and steady hands, they all stood forward. There were John the Constant, of Saxony, Philip of Hesse, George of Brandenburg, and other noble princes, together with deputies from several chief cities. One by one they signed their names to a paper in which they appealed against the violent acts and the errors of the followers of the pope. As they placed their seals to the Protest, they said, We appeal, for ourselves, for our subjects, and for all who re- ceive, or who shall hereafter receive, the word of God.'' Two lawyers of the city then added their names as witnesses, and the deed was done. They had now cut the cords that had bound them to the church of Rome, and were free. It has been said that the upper chamber in Jeru salem, in which the disciples met and continued with one accord in prayer, and that lower chamber in the city of Spire, were " the two cradles of the church." The princes and other reformers returned to the diet, and John the Constant, elector of Saxony, who had first signed the paper, stood before king Ferdinand and the bishops, with the Protest in his hand. And thus he read : — We are resolved, with the grace of God, to maintain the pure preaching of his holy word, such as is contained in the [93] books of the Old and New Testaments, without adding anything thereto that may be contrary to it. This word is the only truth ; it is the sure rule of all doctrine and of all life, and can never fail or de- ceive us. He who builds on this foundation shall stand against all the powers of hell, whilst all the human vanities that are set up against it shall fall before the face of God.,' "We earnestly entreat you,,' they went on to say, to weigh carefully our wrongs and our motives. If you do not yield to our request, we Protest before G-od, our only Creator, Preserver, and Redeemer and Saviour, and who will one day be our Judge, as well as before all men and all creatures, that we, for us and our people, neither consent nor adhere in any manner to the proposed decree'' (which had been made to deprive them of their Christian liberty) "in anything that is con trary to God, to his holy word, to our right con science, and to the salvation of souls.'' King Perdinand wished to return the Protest to those who brought it ) but the princes would not take it back. They placed it on the table, and then respectfully quitted the room. Thus did these bold men act and speak. They did not stand as though they were perplexed or alarmed; but, with the word of God in one hand, and the Protest in the other, they lifted up their heads in courage and hope. 9 [94] This appeal they also sent to the emperor Charles. When the messengers stood before him, he looked upon them in his pride, and speedily sent them from his presence till he should give his decision. After keeping them waiting for a month, he had them put under arrest, and threatened them with death if they left the town or wrote to their friends at Spire.

It was soon found by the reformers that all at- tempts to have the free use of the word of God and liberty of conscience were at an end ; and they pre- pared, in prayer and faith, for the struggle they saw before them. They left the city of Spire re- solved to be Protestants, and to hold fast by the Bible, and the Bible only, as their rule of faith, and their guide to heaven. And from that day to the present the conflict has continued between truth and error—the doctrines of the gospel and the vain devices of popery. Nor will it cease until truth shall prevail, and ,Uhe kingdoms of this world are become the kingdoms of our Lord and of his Christ.', Until that happy time shall come, the young must be taught against what they protest, and why they do so, that they may not bear the name of Protestant in vain. Like the reformers at Spire, they must Protest against all attempts to deprive them of the free use of the Bible; because our Saviour directed the people to search the Scriptures" (John v. 89;) [95] and of Timothy it was said, " From a child thou hast known the Holy Scriptures, which are able to make thee wise unto salvation through faith which is in Christ Jesus.', (2 Tim iii. 15.) They must be Bible Christians, in distinction from those whose faith rests on the word and traditions of men. They must Protest against making the apostle Peter the foundation of the church (though he was one of the chief of the disciples ;) because it is written, Other foundation can no man lay than that is laid, which is Christ Jesus. 1 Cor.

iii. 11. They must Protest against paying Divine worship to the virgin Mary (though she was " blessed among women ;',) because it is declared, Thou shalt worship the Lord thy God, and him only shalt thou serve.'' Matt. iv. 10. They must Protest against praying to saints and angels as mediators; because it is written, "If any man sin, we have an advocate with the Father, Jesus Christ the righteous'' (1 John ii. 1 ;) and there is but one Mediator." 1 Tim. ii. 5. They must Protest against the Papal doctrine of the mass, or the celebration of the Lord's supper as a sacrifice for sin, when a piece of wafer is called the host, or victim," and is worshipped; because such conduct is opposed to the Scripture doctrine "of one sacrifice for sin," which Christ oflered once for all." Heb. x. 10, 12.

[96] They must Protest against the priests withhold- ing the wine from the people at the Lord,s supper; because our Lord said, "Drink ye all of it." Matt, xxvi. 27. They must Protest against the Romish doctrine of human merit ; because the Scriptures teach us, " We are justified freely by his grace through the redemption that is in Christ Jesus', (Rom. iii. 24;) and "if by grace, then is it no more of works. Rom. xi. 6. They must Protest against the vain doctrine of purgatory, or a state in another world in which the remains of sin are cleansed by fire; because it is written, " The blood of Jesus Christ his Son clean- seth us from all sin.', 1 John i. 7. They must Protest against these, and all other errors of the church of Rome; because they* are contrary to the Holy Scriptures, which God has given to us to be the sufficient and only rule of faith and practice. Let the young, then, well con sider why they are called Protestants; and let them be earnest to receive into their hearts those great truths which the apostles and reformers preached, and through the reception of which alone, by the grace of the Holy Spirit leading them to a true faith in Jesus Christ, they can be saved.

THE TRAGEDY OF ST. BARTHOLOMEW'S DAY.

THE LOUVRE, In the Sixteenth Century, from an old print. King Charles the Ninth of France, and his chief officers of State, were in solemn debate in the council chamber of the old palace of the Louvre. They had met on an affair of death ; the death not 9* [98] of one, nor of a few, but of thousands of the peace able inhabitants of the land. On the table before them lay a well-written roll of parchment. It was the register of the noblemen and gentry in France of the reformed or Protestant faith. A strict inquiry had been made through the provinces, that it might contain the names of all. And now the council were planning how and when the deed should be done—a deed which was de- signed to root out, with unsparing hand, the hated Huguenots * from the kingdom. Time and circum stances, it was thought, were favorable. Many of the Protestants had been invited to Paris, under the pretence of being present at the marriage of king Henry of Navarre with a princess of France.

Feasts and sports had been provided for them, and everything was done to lull them into a state of false security.

The young king took up a pen to sign the order for the slaughter, and, casting his half-closed eyes on the ground, with struggling feelings cried, Since it is to be done, take care that no one es- capes to reproach me.', The time fixed on was St. Bartholomew's Day, August 24th, 1572 ; the hour, three o'clock in the * The word Huguenot signifies " associated" or " united together;" it has nearly the same meaning as brethren," one of the titles of the first Christians. Some writers, however, assert that it is derived from the name of the smallest copper coin known in France in the middle ages, and that it was employed as a term of contempt.

[99] morning, when their victims would be sleeping in their beds ; the signal, the tolling of a great bell of one of the churches; the conductor of the murder, the wicked duke of Guise. The gates were ordered to be closed, and the walls secured ; lights were to be hung out from the highest points in the city, that the marks secretly placed on the houses of the doomed might be clearly seen. The soldiers and others were directed to muster shortly after mid night, wearing a piece of white linen on their arms, a white cross on their caps, and the image of the virgin Mary around their necks, lest in the confusion the assassins should be arrayed one against another. Their reward was to be the property of the slain. The armed bands, under the darkness of the night, and with cautious steps, moved to the places assigned to them, ready for their work of blood. In the palace of the Louvre all were wakeful. The king was restless and troubled in his mind. He seemed to start back at the thought of the guilt about to fall on his soul. He would have recalled the order he had given; but his mother, queen Catharine, entered his chamber shortly after mid night, to confirm him in the horrid deed. She then led him to a window, to await the event. And there, until the city clocks struck two, stood a queen mother, encouraging her royal son to commit many thousand murders ! It was one of those calm, lovely nights so com- [100] monlj enjoyed in France in the early autumn. A gentle breeze passed over the garden of the Louvre; and the unnumbered host of stars above seemed, in their soft lustre, to speak only of peace to man. The silence of the night, however, was broken by the report of a pistol. Charles shook with terror, and cold drops stood upon his brow. The sound was answered by the toll of the great bell, when suddenly all the rest of the bells of the churches struck out the signal. The armed men now sprang from their hiding places, shouting, as they rushed along the streets, Kill ! Kill ! Death to the Huguenots V The shrill sounds of the bells, the clatter of arms, the tramp of the assassins, and the shrieks of the dying, soon mingled in one long, loud, terrific sound. The duke of Guise, with his party, first rushed to the house where lay Admiral Coligny, the chief and leader of the Protestants. They found him re- clining on a couch, suffering from a shot m his arm, received a few days before in a base attempt to murder him. The Admiral was aroused from his slumbers by the noise made in breaking open his door. He partly arose from his couch, and com mitted his soul into the hands of God, when one of the soldiers, preparing to strike with his sword, cried, Art not thou the Admiral I am,'' he fearlessly replied ; but, young man, respect these grey hairs, nor stain them with my blood.'' In another moment, regardless of the appeal, the man [101] plunged the sword into his bosom. After receiving the greatest outrages, his body was thrown out of DEATH OF COLIGNY. the window, at the feet of one of the French princes, who, spurning it, cried out, Courage, my friends; we have had a lucky beginning ] let us finish in the [102] same manner." The headless trunk was then drag ged through the streets of Paris, and afterwards hung up by the feet to the common gallows. The young king, as though he had now overcome all scruple and tenderness, went to feast his eyes upon the sight of the body of the man who but a few days before he had called Man pire !—" My father The admiral's son-in-law, lord Teligni, next re- ceived his death-blow, and fell, repeating with his dying lips the names of his wife and children. Other nobles and attendants, with two young chil- dren, were then slain. After having murdered every one in this house, the soldiers went forward on their dreadful purpose. And now arose everywhere the dreadful cry, "Kill! Kill V' The officers of the palace, as they rapidly drove through the streets, cheered on the soldiers with the cry, "Kill every one of them; it is the order of the king.'' The work of destruction was begun in many parts of the city at the same moment.

Open ! by command of the king," was the loud shout of the murderers at the doors of the houses. The unsuspecting Protestants hastened to obey, and were at once cut down. Others, as they raised their windows to see who called them at that hour of the night, were shot. While many, as it was the early morn of the Lord's day, took the tolling of the bells as the call to early prayers. Happy were they who were surprised in their sleep, and who were smitten [103] as they quietly reposed on their beds. Their sufferings were short, while others had their pangs prolonged for hours. Tumults and shrieks increased, until they deep ened into one terrible groan. Pursued on all sides, they were tracked like the poor deer, or driven to the slaughter as a flock of sheep. If they sought refuge in the churches, armed men guarded the doors. If they fled to the palace, in the hope of moving the heart of the king by their piteous cry for mercy, the soldiers awaited them with their spears and guns. If they burst open the prison doors, to conceal themselves among the condemned, they were from thence drawn out to die. They fled to the banks of the river, but they were there caught by boat-hooks, and thrust into the water. Death was everywhere—in their beds, on the house tops, on the water, and on the land—in the palace and in the humblest dwelling. Every spot was a place of slaughter. The assassins spared not the aged, nor women, nor the very babes ! With savage joy they threw the bodies out of the houses, so that there was scarcely a street or lane but was strewn with the dead. The duke Montgomery, with about one hundred Protestant gentlemen, who lodged without the walls, hearing of the murders within the city, sought to escape, half naked, on horseback; but they were overtaken, and all, except about ten of their number, cut to pieces.

[104] Thus, from morning to night, on the Lord's day, this awful slaughter continued, until darkness put an end to the work of blood. The next day it was carried on again. The soldiers were now joined by all the ruffians in the city, who, for the sake of plunder, entered every place where any Huguenot might have hidden himself; and if anyone were found, he was slain, his body stripped, and then cast into the river. In this way, for five days, the slaughter went on, until thousands had fallen in Paris, by the sword, the spear, and the bullet. Messengers were quickly sent to the various pro- vinces and towns, commanding them to follow the example of Paris, in slaying all of the reformed Protestant religion.

At the town of Angers lived a man, beloved for his virtue and learning, named Masson de Rivers, the pastor of the Protestant church. As soon as the king's messenger arrived in the town, he hastened towards the pastor's house, and found him in the garden. I am come to kill thee, by the king's command,', said he, showing his letter of authority.

De Rivers declared his innocence of any offence; but while he was offering a short prayer to Grod, he was shot through the body.

At Lyons, when the letters from the court were brought to Mandelot, (the governor,) he ordered, by sound of trumpet, that all Protestants should appear before him. They, without suspecting his design, obeyed the summons, when they were thrust into [105] the city prisons. He then desired the soldiers to destroy them ; but they refused to direct their arms against men bound and suppliant at their feet. Filled with wrath, the governor hired a number of the vilest men he could find, who, with chopping knives and butchers' axes, fell on the defenceless Huguenots, and, after first mangling their limbs for sport, put an end to their lives. It is recorded, that so great was the slaughter, that the warm blood ran from under the gates of the prisons down the streets, until it mingled with the waters of the neighboring river ! Among those slain in this place were an aged man, named Francis Collut, and his two sons. When Collut saw the murderers come towards him with their axes, he piously said to his children, " Often do such sacrifices happen in Christian churches. Believers in all ages have ever been, and even to the world's end shall be, as sheep among wolves, and doves among hawks.,' Then, embracing each other, and commending their spirits to God, they submitted to the hands of the murderers. They died in each other's arms, and in this state their bodies were afterwards found. In a few of the towns the governors refused to obey the orders of the king. One, named Ortezto, nobly replied : — Sire, I have received your letter enjoining the inhabitants of Bayonne to a massacre of the French Huguenots. Your majesty has many faithful servants and brave soldiers in this city, but 10 [106] not one executioner." The conduct of the Roman Catholic bishop of Bayeux deserves also an honor able record. He not only refused to partake in the slaughter, but protected and provided places of re- fuge for the defenceless Huguenots. One of the officers of state, also, ordered his servants to throw open his gates, as a refuge to the Protestants. He did not long survive after this time ; and his con stant words were, After such horrors I do not wish to live.,' , When the king was told what had been done, he pretended great displeasure. He invited the Pro testants who had escaped to the woods and forests to return to their homes. The poor hunted crea tures, hoping that pity might yet find a place in the heart of the king, obeyed the royal command. But in about two days they were seized, and the hand of murder again was raised against them. During this time king Charles was not only a witness of the sad sights from the windows of his palace, but it is said he even fired on some men who were try ing to escape. The sight of blood had quenched whatever pity at first he may have felt, and aroused the worst passions of his heart. " For thirty days together,,' says an account written the year after the massacre, there was no end of killing, slaying, and robbing; so that at this day there are thousands of little babes and children, that were well born, now fatherless and motherless, [107] and in beggary." De Thou, a Papal historian, states the number slain throughout France, on this occasion, to have been thirty thousand; other ac- counts give from sixty thousand to one hundred thousand. The messenger who carried the news to Rome was rewarded with a thousand crowns. And the pope joyfully cried aloud, " Good news ! good news V Guns were fired at the castle of St. Angelo, and bon fires blazed in the public streets. A solemn proces sion was formed of the popes, cardinals, and officers of state, who, in the church of St. Mark, wickedly offered up thanks to God for the " uprooting of the heretics.'' To keep up the memory of the event, the pope ordered a medal to be struck. On one side was the portrait of the pope ; on the other, a de- stroying angel holding a cross in one hand, and a sword in the other, with which he is slaying the Protestants; and on this medal were the words, " Ugonottorum strages," ,Hhe slaughter of the [108] Huguenots." Thus has the church of Rome pre- served the evidence of its own crimes. Whatever king Charles of France hoped to gain by destroj'ing his Protestant subjects, he was miser- ably disappointed. The short remnant of his days was a fulfilment of Scripture : " Whoso rewardeth evil for good, evil shall not depart from his house." Prov. xvii. 13. His kingdom was disturbed, the confidence of his people was lost, and his own family were in a continual state of strife. Ever after the massacre of St. Bartholomew's day his counte- nance was marked with a settled gloom, or with a flush he had never before worn, arising from the hauntings of a guilty conscience within. He gradually sank under a slow internal fever, that wasted his strength. In his last hours he endured frightful agonies, and he died miserably, at the age of only twenty-four.

As we think of this unhappy prince sinking into an early grave, oppressed by the horrors of an accusing conscience, are we not reminded of the words of Holy Scripture ? The wicked plottetli against the just ; they have drawn out the sword, and have bent their bow, to slay such as be of up right conversation. Their sword shall enter into their own heart, and their bows shall be broken.'' Psa. xxxvii. 12—15. How long shall all the workers of iniquity boast themselves ? They break in pieces thy people, [109] 0 Lord, and afflict thine heritage. —But the Lord shall bring upon them their own iniquity, and shall cut them off in their own wickedness. Psa. xciv.

4, 23. Such persecution has often been, in ages past, the lot of the true church of God : but amidst all the cruelties that have raged against it in the world, God has ever preserved to himself a people. Well has it been said that the blood of the martyrs is the seed of the church. It was so in France ; for as these pious men were cut off, others arose in their place. Many of the people, beholding their holy lives, and the peace with which they met the most cruel deaths, were led to renounce former errors, and "to inquire after the way of salvation through the Lord Jesus Christ.

10*

THE FLIGHT OF THE HUGUENOTS.

About two hundred and fifty years ago, there was great joy in the dwellings of the Protestants in France. The news had spread over the land that the king had, while in the city of Xantes, sent out a decree in favor of the persecuted. They had passed many long years of trouble ; their places of worsUp had been broken down ; their ministers sent out of the land, and many of their friends had been slain. But henceforth they were to have the free exercise of their religion and the rights of citizens. Their sick poor were to be allowed to enter the pub lic hospitals, and other privileges of the kind were to be fully enjoyed. They were a loyal and thank ful people, and they welcomed these benefits with gratitude to the king, and with ruany praises to God.

The Protestants were now at liberty to attend to trade, and the care of the land. Their peaceful and active habits soon made them well known. Xo looms made finer silk, no ploughs were more busy in the fields, and no vines were more fruitful than theirs. They soon became the best workpeople in [111] the country. And this was as it should be ; for the purest faith should always be connected with in- dustry and attention to the duties of life. Henry the Good," as the king was called, had been once a Protestant; but he changed his religion to obtain an earthly crown. Many mourned that he should have forgotten the example and counsel of a pious mother : still he did not quite neglect the friends of his early youth. He knew their worth, and did much to serve them. His merciful conduct did not please the Papists, and one day he was stabbed by a wretched priest while riding in his carriage in the city of Paris. The Protestants soon found that the next king who came to the throne bore no love towards them ; and they had to suffer many hardships. At length, Louis the Four teenth revoked the edict given in the city of Nantes, although it had been declared that it should never be altered. When it suited the purpose of the Pa pists, they did not scruple to break all the laws which showed any kind of favor to the Protestants, even when they had been secured to them by the most solemn oaths and pledges.

And now, instead of joy, there was only mourn ing and sorrow in many of the castles and cottages of France. The enemies of the truth had obtained the power they wanted, and they were at liberty to oppress as they pleased. Severe laws were passed, in the hope of rooting out the reformed religion.

[112] Heavy fines were laid upon those who did not adorn their houses on saints' days, and heavy blows if they did not kneel when a Papal procession went along the streets. They were not allowed to be doctors, booksellers, printers, or even grocers. No apprentice could be taught a trade in their shops. If they were heard to sing hymns in public or private, they were sent to prison ; their psalm book was publicly burned ; and the Bible was taken out of their houses. Their places of worship were again broken into and destroye(i ; their ministers were sent out of the land, or shut up in jail. The sick could only be attended by Papal priests ; and the bodies of those who died were often torn out of their graves, and left to be devoured by wolves and vultures. The distress of the Huguenots was at its height, when they saw their dear children torn from their arms, and carried away to be brought up as Papists.

The joy of watching over them, of hearing their simple little prayers, and of telling them of the love of Christ in dying on the cross for sinners, was no more to be known by them. And theirs was the bitter grief of not knowing whether their beloved ones were faithful to the truth or had denied it, whether they were suffering torture in a monastery or nunnery, or laid in the quiet grave. Times of trial show who truly love the Lord Jesus Christ. It was so now. Many who were [113] once known as Protestants forsook the faith of their fathers. Some were gained over with titles and honors, others with promises of reward ; many from fear of a dungeon and death ; and numbers were bribed with large sums. The common people were offered a freedom from taxes for two yearS; besides a gift of money, if they would change their religion within one month. Those who would not turn were to pay double taxes and a fine of ten pounds— a large sum in those days. The effect was that many denied their Lord, some from terror, and others from hope of such a reward as the wicked could give. Happy did those think themselves who could make their escape to other lands, even though they left behind them all their worldly goods.

There were sad sights in those days, and those had hard hearts who did not shed tears at the suf- ferings of the afflicted Christians who had remained faithful in evil times. One scene was beheld in a little country town which made many weep. The good Protestant pastor was to have his limbs broken upon a wheel—one of the most painful deaths that could be endured. His enemies did not destroy life at once ; they seemed to take delight in adding to his sufferings. For two days he was left in the deepest agony on the wheel. In the midst of his pain he thus spoke to those who stood by : Jesus Christ has satisfied for my sins, and not only for mine, but for the sins of all those who shall go to [114] * him by faith, as now I do. I cast myself upon the merits and death of Jesus, and cling to him as my Saviour and Redeemer. My dear people, receive my last farewell, and know that I preached to you the pure truths of the gospel—the true way that leads to heaven. Among others who were faithful were a gentle- man and his wife. A number of soldiers were sent to their mansion. They rudely burst open the doors, carried off some of their goods, and sold them. . They then made stables of the beautiful rooms, and caused their horses to lie upon the rich beds. When the ruin of the house was at an end, the master of it went forth with his wife, leading by the hand four little children under seven years of age. As they passed out at the doors their persecutors threw upon them from the windows pitchers of water. TTet and cold, they went forth without a home and with- out food. After a short journey they came to a friend's house, where they were taken in, and in the first night of this distress the mother had another little infant born. But there was to be no shelter allowed for these pious outcasts. A band of soldiers traced them to the spot, and drove them out—with the baby, only three days old, in its mother's arms I After years of trial, this family found a happy home in England.

Many an interesting story of the flight of the Huguenots has been preserved. A family who saw [115] that there could be no peace in their own land, planned a way for their escape. They first conceal- ed their money, jewels, and other valuables in quilt ed silk petticoats, secretly worked by the lady and her daughter, and which they sent to England. The two eldest sons had already contrived to leave the country ; there remained now the parents, a daughter aged sixteen, and two little boys of four and six years old. Just as they were all ready to start, the father was betrayed and carried to prison. Those he loved hastened to visit him, when he urged them to flee to a place of safety, in the hope that the time would come when he should be able to join them again. His wife, attended by a male servant, went in disguise to a sea-port, and there arranged for a passage to England for herself and three children. She then concealed herself in a house, while the servant went back to bring the children. The eld est daughter, dressed as a peasant girl, placed her young brothers each in a pannier or basket, which was slung across the back of a donkey. She then well covered over the little boys with fruits and veg etables, and on the top of all some poultry in a basket were placed. The children had been charged, whatever should happen by the way, on no account to speak or move. We shall see how bravely these little ones behaved in their trying condition. The servant, in the dress of a country farmer, rode first on horseback. He moved in advance, as if he were unknown to the girl with the donkey ; though [116] he took care to keep in sight as she went along the road. The young refugee daughter traveled at night ; but as time was precious, the latter part of the journey had to be taken by daylight. Mingled hope and grief filled her mind, as she either thought of going to her mother and escaping to a land of liberty, or of the sorrows of her dear father, left behind in his dreary prison. While on the road she was alarmed at the sight of a party of horse THE FLIGHT OF THE HUGUENOTS.

soldiers riding towards her. They fixed their eye upon her, and then at the panniers. " What is in those baskets?', they cried. Before she could give [117] an answer, one of them drew his sword, and thrust it into the pannier in which the younger child was hid. No cry was heard ; no resistance was made.

The soldiers concluded that all was right, and turn- ing round, galloped quickly down the road. As soon as they were out of sight the sister seized the pannier, and threw off the upper part of its contents, expecting to find her little brother killed. As he lifted up his arms towards his terrified sister, she saw he was covered with blood from a severe cut on one of them. The child in the hour of danger, shut up in his basket-prison, knew that if he cried, his own life and the lives of his brother and sister would be lost, and he bravely bore the pain and was silent. The sister bound up the wound as best she could, and nursed him on the road with the fondest care, and had the joy of finding that his life was spared, though he carried a scar from the wound all his days. After a perilous journey the young refugees safe- ly reached the seaside. They secretly got on board a ship, whose sails were soon spread to the wind ; and in a few days they safely landed in England.

But the father never followed them. Year after year passed away, and there was the poor captive, though not all the time in a dungeon, yet under restraint and unable to join those he loved. They never met again on earth : may we not believe that, through 11 [118] the merits of the Saviour, they all had a joyful meeting before the throne of God in heaven ? Many were the plans of the persecuted Huguenots for escaping out of their "house of bondage," as it was called. They dared not leave their homes dressed for a journey, as they would be at once sus- pected, for they were strictly watched. Early in the morning, or late in the evening, they passed from their doors gaily dressed, with a cane in hand, as if going out for a short walk, or on a visit to a friend. Some went forth as hunters, with a dog running before them, and a gun over their shoulder. A few miles from their homes they changed their clothes—perhaps they put on the disguise of a miller, with a sack of corn on the back; or of a peasant driving some cattle before them ; or of a porter with a loaded truck going to market. Sometimes a nobleman exchanged clothes with his servant ; the former waited at table, assisted in the kitchen, cleaned the horses, and slept in a gar ret, while the real serving man lived in the best room of the house, and went to rest on its softest bed. Those who were too poor to adopt these methods, traveled at night—their food was chiefly wild berries gathered by the way; and in the day they rested in the shelter of woods and caverns, with a stone for their pillow. The women also passed in disguise, wheeling barrows or carrying a load. On [119] their perilous way they were exposed to rain, snow, and cold. Rivers were crossed by swimming; mountains were climbed, and miry swamps were passed, until a place of safety was reached. That refuge attained, their first act was to cast them selves upon their knees, and there to offer thanks to Grod for delivering them from the ,Hion's mouth." The new home of these poor refugees was mostly across the sea, in England. As soon as they reached the coast, they sought some kind ship-captain, who hid them in his vessel under bales of goods and heaps of coals, or in empty casks, where they had only the bung-hole through which to breathe. A Protestant nobleman, with forty persons, crossed the channel in the depth of winter, in a very small vessel, hardly large enough to hold them. They were overtaken by a storm, and were out at sea without food for days, their only support being a little melted snow, with which they tried to satisfy their burning thirst, until they landed half dead on the shores of England.

A husband and his wife tried to escape. They each took a different road, to avoid suspicion. The man was caught and carried to prison, but the wife reached the English shores, where she anxiously awaited her husband. To force the poor man to renounce his religion his jailers placed him in a dungeon with an iron floor, and no seat or means of [120] support. Under this was a strong fire. The iron floor was then slowly heated, until the feet of the prisoner were so fearfully burnt as to make him a cripple for life. When they grew weary of tor- menting, the poor Huguenot was left to go about the town on crutches—a misery to himself, and an object of pity to all beholders. Years passed away, when one day a poor aged Frenchman was seen hobbling about the streets of London. In broken English he asked the passers- by to tell him where he could find his wife. Some could not understand his words; and those who could were yet unable to aid him in his search. All he could tell them was that he was in search of his wife—his Louise." As he crept along one after- noon, with the constant inquiry on his lips, some one directed him to a coffee-house near Soho Square, kept by a French refugee. It was the resort of the Huguenots, many of whom by this time had turned their skill to good account in busy London.

To this coffee-house the poor cripple made his way; but no one there knew his wife. " She might be alive," said they, "or she might be dead.', It seemed as if her name was now unknown on the earth. In the corner sat a pedlar : he listened to what was said, but made no reply. Yet were there kind ly thoughts and feelings in his heart. He had come to London to lay in a stock of goods; and [121] as, on his return to the country, he would pass through some towns where the French had found a home, why, thought he, could he not make in- quiry if any one knew of the poor cripple's wife. As he pursued his way from place to place, he ceased not to feel an interest in the sad story he had heard in that coffee-house in London. At length, he came to Canterbury, where he knew many refugees followed the trades of jewelers and wax-bleachers. He sought among them for any one who might answer to the missing wife. The strange tale soon got spread about, and it led to a 11* [122] delightful result. For there, indeed, lived the poor woman, getting her living by needlework. She had long given up the hope of seeing her dear hus- band again : surely he was a galley-slave, or in some dungeon, or dead. But now the pedlar's story reach- ed her ears, and she set off without delay for Lon don. There she soon found her aged afflicted hus- band, who had been reduced to the lowest poverty, and was in utter despair of finding her he had so earnestly sought. It was a meeting of mingled joy and sorrow. She rejoiced to behold again the com panion of her youth, and the professor of the same faith ; but tears flowed fast as she beheld his help less state. After a short stay, they set out for Can terbury, where the faithful wife worked hard, and nursed, and cherished the cripple-husband whom she had often mourned as dead. Another Huguenot couple resolved to flee. They could disguise themselves, but what was to be done with their baby ? If they were seen passing through the gates of the town in which they lived, with a child, they would at once be seized. After many thoughts, their plan was to wrap the infant as a formless bundle, to one end of which they attached a string. They then took advantage of a very deep gutter, like that which runs in the middle of so many old streets in French towns. When night came, the gates of the place were, as usual, closed fast. Now was the time. The living bundle was [123] duly placed in the gutter, near to one of the gates, with many a prayer that the sleeping draught would not be too strong, and yet so strong as to keep the child asleep. The parents knocked at the gate, as though they wished to pass into the country. The guard came out of his little house, and well surveyed them. He knew they were Huguenots ; but where, thought he, is their child ? Will a Huguenot mother desert her tender babe, that she may escape? Will she leave it to be brought up as a Papist? Not she; so then the guard concluded that they were not about to flee — at least this time. He turned the heavy lock ; they passed out ; and now again securing the gates, he slowly turned into his guardroom. " Hush ! quick ! quick ! catch the end of the string under the gate: There ! it is caught. Now, gently draw it along in the shadow.,' Blessed be the name of God, the babe is through. It has not cried. The sleeping draught has done its work.

The infant is once again in its mother's arms; and the parents, with their dear treasure, are on their way to the sea-shore. That couple, with their babe, in a few days were safely in England, and their descendants may read this story on the page that recounts the adventures of their Huguenot fore- fathers. The new home of these poor refugees, as we have said, was mostly in England. There were [124] many of all ranks in this land wlio felt for their sorrows ; they opened their houses to receive them, and their purses to aid them in their need. But the refugees came not to eat the bread of idleness. They carried with them their skill and their trades. Thousands made their way to London, and formed almost a new town in the part of the outskirts known as Spitalfields ; and others founded a colony at St. Giles-in-the-Fields. Some went to Norwich, Coventry, Canterbury, Edinburgh, and other places.

Among the refugees in England were a duke, a duchess, several generals, counts, marquises, vis- counts, barons, judges, noble ladies, men of learning, ministers, merchants, and captains.

There were also farmers and artisans. They brought with them the useful arts of life as well as the example of their piety. ' The weaving of silk was their chief employment ; and soon their busy looms were heard in many a dwelling. Even noblemen became master weavers ; for though, in some instances, they had saved enough out of the wreck of their estates to provide for themselves, they engaged in trade to help their companions in tribulation." Before this time, the people of Eng land had to send abroad for many valuable articles; but now they could obtain them home-made. The French introduced into their adopted country the art of calico-printing and wax-bleaching ; the weav ing of velvet, silk stockings, crapes, bombazines, [125] gauzes, damask table-linen, cambric, and other things of the kind. Besides, they brought with them improved ways of manufacturing ribbons, tapestry, baize, sail-cloth, and sacking ; new modes also of dyeing, and making hats, pins, needles, watches, lace, and looking-glasses. Some were skilful as artists, and some in science. The first person who contrived a machine in England moved by steam was Savary ; the best maker of telescopes was Dolland ; and the most famous biscuit-baker was Le Man, all belonging to refugee families. In these ways they repaid England for its protection ; and to the present day the people of that country gather the fruits of the toils, losses, and sufferings, the skill and the industry of those driven from their native land, for conscience' sake, by the base and and cruel act which revoked the Edict of Nantes.

THE GUNPOWDER PLOT.

It was towards the end of the month of October, 1605, that lord Monteagle arrived at his country house in the village of Hoxton, a mile or two beyond the old walls of London. King James had issued an order for the parliament to assemble in a few days from this time; and the nobility and [138] gentry had arrived from their more distant dwell- ings in the counties, to those they owned in or near the city of Westminster.

The village of Hoxton in those days was noted for the mansions of the rich and noble. Fields of corn enclosed by hawthorn hedges, and shady lanes, whose green banks were adorned in their season with the primrose and daffodil, were seen on every side. In one direction were the mansions of earls and lords, whose turrets and towers were beheld from afar. In another appeared groups of pretty cottage-homes, where latticed porches were adorned with creeping roses, fragrant jasmine, white elder flowers, and the trailing honeysuckle. While ad- joining the moor (now known as Moorfields) long rows of pollard and chestnut trees lined the grounds, or shooting-buts, where the London archers at the close of the day displayed their skill at the long bow.

Lord Monteagle had i«nvited some friends to supper on Saturday evening, October 26th. As they sat together in the great oaken hall, just as the evening shades had closed around, a serving man entered with a letter in his hand. From whence does it come inquired the lord. The servant could not tell. All he knew was, that as he stood at the great gate of the house, a tall man, with a broad hat slouched over his face, and a cloak thrown so as to conceal his form, had suddenly come from [139] behind a cluster of treeS; and without speaking a word, had placed the letter in his hand. He had then (juickly withdrawn, under the shadows of the twilight.

The lord Monteagle carelessly tossed the letter to a gentleman who was near him, and desired him to read it aloud. The writing was large and cramped ; it needed care to make out its contents. It spoke of some startling event about to happen. Think not slightly of this advertisement," said the letter, "but retire yourself into the country, where you may expect the event in safety ; for though there be no appearance of any stir, they shall receive a terrible blow this parliament, yet they shall not see who hurts them." In earnest words it proceeded : This counsel is not to be contemned, because it may do you good, and do you no harm, for the danger is passed as soon as you have burnt this letter.'' The letter had no name to it ; from whom could it come ? No place or date was marked upon it ; where and when was it written ? Its words were dark, strange, and solemn; to what could they refer? They surely meant more than they ex pressed, and their admonition was not to be slighted.

Early the next morning, lord Monteagle left Hoxton to meet the earl of Salisbury, the lord high treasurer of England, to whom the letter was [140] shown. They then went together to the king.

The matter seemed of sufficient importance to lead to the calling of a council of nobles, and before them the strange lines were placed. The king argued it could not be a public outbreak that was meant, for the words were— There shall be no appearance of any stir;', yet it was to be " Si terri- ble blow," though by some invisible agent, for they, "were not to see who should hurt them ;" and the deed was to be quickly done. Now, the king's father, Darnley, the husband of Mary, queen of Scots, had been destroyed by gunpowder, and it was at once concluded that an explosion of that com bustible was intended by the dark words of the letter. Let us now pass to Enfield Chase, a few miles to the north of Hoxton. The spot at this period of time was wild, lonely, and Avoody, and but little visited except by hunters. An old house stood near a wood, called White Webbs ; and here, in a small room, had met a band of men to agree upon a dark deed of murder. One w,as named Robert Catesby; his mind had formed the plot, and he was looked upon by the rest as the leader. The others were named Winter, Digby, Tresham, Rookwood, Keys, Wright, and Percy. They were all men in the rank of gentlemen : some were rich, and all were Roman Catholics. But one of the number, Guy Fawkes, [141] was to be the chief agent in the design. He had been a soldier, and was calm, bold, and desperate.

He had lived long in other lands, and, a bigot to his religion, he thought it a work of merit to de- stroy the lives of Protestants. These men had often met before ; sometimes in the fields near London, at other times in a little house on the banks of the river Thames, at Erith. Several months had passed away, and they had been waiting for a time when the nobles of the land, with the king and young princes, should meet to- gether for business of the State. It was their hor rid intention to blow up the whole into the air, and thus at a stroke to rid themselves of the chief friends of the Protestant faith, and prepare the way for setting up of the papal religion ! What could have brought these men to imagine and contrive so wicked a plot ? Some of them had been fined and opposed for their religion 3 but right views of Christian liberty were not much known and understood in those days. Yet the injury they had received, however occasioned or however un justifiable, could never warrant the dreadful revenge they were about to take. That men of fortune and education should unite in such a wicked design is truly strange ; but they had long brooded over it, until the sinfulness of the deed was forgotten.

Perhaps they had been made bold to attempt it by a brief, or letter of authority, which the pope of 13 [142] Rome had sent to England, in which they were told only to obey a popish king, and that it was for the honor of God and the good of their own souls to re sist a Protestant sovereign. Whatever it was that had filled their hearts with thoughts of murder and treason, they now placed themselves on their knees, and took a solemn oath not to betray or forsake one another. Gerard, a priest, performed mass, gave them the sacrament to sustain their courage in the enterprise, and to impart to the deed the sanction of their false religion.

As some months had passed since they first con- ceived the wicked plot, Percy had become impatient.

Well, gentlemen,', he said, " shall we always talk, and never do It was, however, felt by his companions that the time had not yet come. They must proceed with care, that they might the better make sure of their purpose. They had already hired two houses, one next to the parliament house, and another at a distance, in which they had stored barrels of gunpowder and large piles of wood. At the former place seven of these men had been digging and working in the hope of getting through the walls to form a mine.

They had dug deep below the cellar, but the walls of the parliament house were three feet thick, and resisted all their attempts. It was hard work for those who had been brought up as gentlemen. Guy Fawkes stood at the door as sentinel. When the [143] footsteps of a passenger in the street were heard, a signal was given, and the digging ceased until the stranger was out of sight. Thus very slowly they went on. They were all well armed, and were re- solved, should they be discovered, to die rather than surrender. A store of provisions was obtained : hard eggs, dried meats, and such other food as would keep, were in the vault, that they might awaken no suspicion from the going in and out to purchase food. Though they had toiled hard and long, the trait- ors made but little way. Again and again they stopped, as though it were hopeless to proceed. And then at times they were startled by a noise, as of a tolling bell, and by other strange sounds, which seemed to come out of the earth. " Is it a warn ing,' ' they said one to another, " that our own fu- neral bell will shortly toll But they tried to quiet their fears, and sprinkled on the wall some holy water,'' which they had obtained from a Papal priest. And as again and again they imagined they heard the tolling of a bell, they as often resorted to the holy water" for protection and help. Bold as they were, conscience often spoke and awoke alarm in their breasts. How true it is, " The wicked flee when no man pursueth : but the righteous are bold as a lion," Prov. xxviii. 1. A poet says, " 'Tis conscience that makes cowards of us all." [144] There can be no peace found in the way of guilt.

Still, Satan and their own wicked hearts urged the plotters forward in their dreadful course. One day, while they were working in the mine, they heard a rumbling noise above them. They were alarmed—had they been discovered ? No ; it was only a man named Bright, a coal-dealer, who was shovelling his coals into sacks, to carry them away, as he was about to remove from the cellar under the parliament house to some other spot. They learned that the cellar he was leaving was to be let. How well timed it seemed, for it was just the spot they wanted. It was exactly beneath the hall wherein the king would meet the nobility of the land. Percy was quickly sent to hire it, under the pretence that it was to be used for storing wood and coals. Into this cellar they brought in small quantities, and secretly at night, to the extent of thirty-six barrels of gugapowder. Large stones, blocks of wood, and bars of iron were also brought hither, and laid among the barrels, to give greater force to the explosion, and make it more destructive to human life. Over all was cast a covering of wood.

Everything now seemed ready for the fatal mo ment. What could prevent them doing their deed?

They had been all faithful one to another; they were united and resolved ; no one had a suspicion of the plot; all matters hitherto se,ed to be favorable to it.

[145] GUY FAWKES' CELLAR.-, The conspirators knew that there would be at the opening of the parliament several of their own friends ; could anything be done to save them ? Keys wished to give warning to one of the lords not to be present, for he had given food and shelter to his wife and children when once they were in distress. Percy sought to save an earl who was his kinsman.

Tresham wanted to spare two lords who had married his sisters, and who were strong Papists. Hence * In laying the foundation for the New Houses of Parliament at Westminster, it was found necessary to remove this cellar, which for many ages had been associated with the dark deeds of Guy Fawkes.

[146] their meeting at White Webbs to decide this mat ter. Catesby, however, tried to prove to them that most, or all, of the Roman Catholics would be ab sent. " But with all that," said he, rather than the project shall not take effect, if they were as dear to me as my own son, they also must be blown up." But, unknown to the rest, Tresham had already sent a letter to lord Monteagle. It was that strange letter which we have seen delivered at the house at Hoxton by the tall stranger towards the close of the day.

The conspirators had their last meeting in a retired walk in Lincoln,s Inn Fields, where they debated on the chance of the plot being known to the government. Some by this time had become fearful, and said they were all lost men, and had better save themselves by instant flight. Others sought to sustain the courage of their companions ; by assuring them that all was safe and certain, and so they parted again.

That evening the lord chamberlain, whose duty it was to see that all things were ready for the meeting of the king and his lords, came to the parliament house along with lord Monteagle. They appeared, as if by accident, to descend to the cel lars. As they opened the doors of the one where the gunpowder was placed, they saw a dark tall man standing near to a pile of wood. It was Guy [147] Fawkes, whose nerve and boldness did not even then forsake him. The lord chamberlain, in an apparently careless manner, asked who he was. " I am servant to Mr. Percy/ , was the quiet answer, and have the care of his coals.'' " Your master,'' said the chamberlain, ,' has laid in a good stock of fuel." As the visitors turned themselves to go up the stairs, Guy Fawkes in bold confidence concludes All is right : still undiscovered." The lord chamberlain reported the results of his search to the king's council. All agreed that the quantity of fuel was much greater than could be wanted by Percy, who had not been known to reside near the spot. Let the cellar be searched again to-night," was the order given ; and an officer and some guards were to be ready for the purpose. The evening before the meeting of parliament arrived. Catesby and some of the conspirators had gone into the country to raise a rebellion as soon as the king and the parliament were blown into the air. Others had taken their place on the lofty ground near Highgate, from which place they ob- tained a distant prospect of the roof of the House of Lords. They were all ready to start at a moment's notice, to carry out their wretched design in their several ways, as had been arranged. Guy Fawkes took his place in the cellar, with calm determination. He had received mass at the hands of the priest, and doubted not of success. His dark lantern, with [148] a light in it, was behind the door ; a train of gun powder was carefully laid from the barrels to the entrance ; the slow-burning matches and the touch- wood were at hand. He had a watch, a scarce article in those days, which was only possessed by persons of rank and wealth—that he might know the exact moment when to light the train. A ship lay not far off in the river, prepared to sail as soon as the deed was done, to carry him to another land. A horse was saddled to convey him to the ship ; and, booted and spurred, he awaited the fatal in- stant when the light should be applied to the train. The clock of Westminster Abbey struck twelve, and the morning of the 5th of November had begun.

The streets were all silent. Two o,clock soon came round, and Guy Fawkes softly and slowly opened the door of the cellar, and stepped out to look about him, and to revive himself with the fresh air. But he had scarcely placed his feet in the street, when an officer made a sudden plunge and seized him by the shoulder. He struggled for a moment to get back into the cellar, that he might apply a light to the train, and blow himself and the officers of justice into the air; but others rushed upon him and cast him on the ground. They soon bound him hand and foot, and, after a fierce conflict, carried him away to a place of security.

The news rapidly spread through the city that [149] king James and his parliament had escaped from the fearful and wicked plot. Shortly after day break, Guy Fawkes was brought before the lords of the council, confessed to the whole deed so far as himself was concerned, and gloried in it, though he refused to tell the names of his companions.

Early in the next morning, the prisoner was traitors' gate, tower of LONDON. conveyed to the Tower of London ; and under the gloomy arch of Traitor's Gate was conveyed to his cell. After a long trial he was condemned, and at [150] the west end of St. PauFs churchyard paid the penalty of his crime by the forfeit of his life. The conspirators stood hour after hour on High gate hill, during the early morning of the 5th of November ; then through the day, expecting to see the dire explosion ; but a messenger brought them word that Guy Fawkes was arrested. At once they fled with teiTor and in confusion. Some seized horses that they found on the road, and passed from place to place, till they came to Holbeach, a large man sion on the borders of Staffordshire. There they made a stand, and resolved to fortify the house, and await their death. As they were getting together their means of defence, a bag of gunpowder exploded, burning several of the plotters very severely.

This seemed to them a judgment from heaven for their wickedness. Catesby himself began to fear that God was angry with them, and he and others confessed that their deeds were cruel and sinful be fore God. In a short time the sheriff of the county, with an armed band, reached the house, and suri'ounded it. In the king's name they summoned the rebels to surrender. A short fight followecf, when one of them was disabled by an arrow from a cross-bow. Two others were soon stretched on the ground in dying agony. Catesby and Percy placed themselves back to back in an attitude of defiance, when one of the sheriff's men fired at them with a doubly [151] loaded musket, and they fell. Catesby crawled into a corner of the room, and died ; the other lingered till the next day. The rest of the party were soon overpowered, and made prisoners. They were brought to trial, and in due course were executed for their treason. All loyal and pious hearts were filled with horror while they rejoiced at the wonderful deliverance which God had wrought. The young daughter of the king, the princess Elizabeth, only eight years old, thus wrote to her brother, the youthful prince of Wales : My dear brother, I doubt not that you have rendered thanksgiving to our gracious God for the deliverance which he has vouchsafed to us, as I have also done, and still do on my own account ; but I wish to join your vows to my own, and to say with you, ,If the Lord be for us, who shall be against us? While he keeps me I will not fear what man can do., Such is the brief record of the Gunpowder Plot.In the discovery of this popish design we see how true it is that God will bring to light the hidden things of darkness;" for His eyes are in every place, beholding the evil and the good." Sinners, and all their wicked purposes, are known to him. We may say in the words of the psalmist : — [152] " They encourage themselves in an evil matter : They commune of laying snares privily ; They say, Who shall see them? They search out iniquities ; They accomplish a diligent search: Both the inward thought of every one of them, and the heart, is deep. But God shall shoot at them with an arrow; Suddenly shall they be wounded. So they shall make their own tongue to fall upon them selves ; — And all men shall fear, and shall declare the work of God." PsA. Ixiv. 5—9.

THE STORY OF THE ENGLISH BIBLE.

The Sabbath sun rises and sets, bringing to our hearts and homes unnumbered blessings. The gospel is preached to thousands; and hosts of children, in the quiet of their own dwellings, or amid the cheerful hum of the Sunday-school, read the holy book of God. We may apply to these times the prophecy of old : They shall sit every man under his vine and under his fig-tree; and none shall make them afraid,', Micah iv. 4. But how seldom do we remember the wearisome labors, and the long and deadly struggles of holy men in former ages, in their efforts that the people might have, in all its freeness and fullness, a cheap and open Bible. We will go back in our thoughts to other times, and, with grateful feelings, trace the steps which led to this blessed result. It was in the year 1428, or thereabouts, a man, named Lawrence Coster, was seen walking on the outside of the walls of the old city of Haarlem, in Holland. His pace was slow, and it was evident [168] that his mind was engaged in deep thought. As he walked, he came to a grove, and there with his knife he cut a piece of bark from a tree. He paced up and down beneath the shade of the grove, and amused himself with carving the bark. Now and then he paused, and then again went on with his work. As he turned to go home he found he had cut the shape of a number of raised letters on the face of the bark. That evening he sat down in his house, and carved more letters on other pieces of wood. When he had done several in this way he fastened them together by a piece of string. Some ink was then made thick, and rubbing the faces of the letters with it, he pressed a sheet of paper against them. He gazed on what he had done with surprise, and well he might. To him it was the first idea of printing. He had made the earliest attempt, in Europe at least, of impressing on paper the thoughts of the mind. There was hope for the world in those pieces of bark tied together by a string.

A few years passed away, and anothej man, of the name of Gottenberg, was busy in a small work shop in the German city of Mentz, cutting letters. This time, however, they were not made of wood or bark, but of metal. Nor were several carved on one piece of wood, each was a separate type, or letter. Something of a machine, too, called a press, had been formed, and with these metal types he soon set [169] about printing books. The volume that was print- ed was a Latin Bible. It was not finished, as it would be now, in a few weeks ; but nearly eight years passed before it came from the workmen's hands. Every one who saw it was astonished. Copy after copy was sent forth, all exactly alike, and it seemed as if they had been produced by miracle. Who could write them so fast? How could they be made so rapidly ? Why was it that they all appeared alike—page for page, line for line, the same to the smallest dot ? Men knew but little of this infant art, nor did they foresee, in its first efibrts, the earnest of the richest blessings to all mankind. Surely, it was well that the first volume thus printed was the best book—that it was God's book. It was the pledge of the great things to be done by the discovery of the art of printing, in giving the Holy Scriptures to every nation on the earth. Let us now trace another step in the course that led to a free and full Bible for the people.

England was to receive the benefit of the new art, in conveying to it the Scriptures in the lan- guage of the people, through the means of William Tyndale. This worthy man was born on the bor- ders of Wales, of parents who were in a humble con dition of life. How little did they think, as they looked on him in his infancy, that he would become 15* [170] one of the best friends of his country, and that his name would be held by many in more honor than any conqueror who ever lived ! In the course of time, William Tyndale became a poor priest of one of the colleges in Oxford. As he sat one day with some fellow priests, he spoke of the value of the word of God, when they mockingly said, We are better without Grod's law than the pope's law.'' To which Tyndale replied : " If God spare me, before many years I will cause a boy that driveth a plough to know more of the Scriptures than you do." The young priest saw that the people were living and dying without Bible knowledge, deceived by the vain doctrines of the church of Rome, and he quietly resolved to get the New Testament printed in English for the use of all. This was a good and great thought—a bold and daring thought—for a poor man to cherish ; yet, with the help of God, he was resolved to make the attempt. He was not content to plan and arrange this important work, but with labor and patience he sought to carry it forward. Tyndale had heard of the learning and riches of the bishop of London, and in his simplicity he thought he would surely aid him in the pious de- sign ; but he soon found that there was ,' no room in my lord of London's palace to translate the word of God, nor any safe place to do it in all England.', [171] At this time there lived in London a pious and wealthy merchant, named Monmouth, who had been taught the truth through reading the books of the reformers in Germany. He was a kind friend to Tyndale, and gave him a room in his house, where the good priest used to sit, night and day, busy with his pen and Latin Bible. But these were times of danger to those who truly feared Grod. Tyndale, therefore, well supplied with money by his liberal patron, set sail over the North Sea, and went to the great city of Hamburg. Then, removing to Cologne, he went on in the translation and printing of the New Testament, until ten sheets were done. Two pious friends. Frith and Roye, * assisted Tyndale in the translation. There they sate, day by day, in an old-fashioned room in an obscure street in the city of Cologne. Pens, parchment, and paper were before them ; one read the Latin Bible, a second the Greek, and the third wrote down the words of the sacred text in English. In about a year this work was finished. Tyndale then found a printer who was willing to print it. This was a service full of danger. Popish priests were on the alert to find out any who aided the reformers , in their work. But onward the printing went. In this state of things, an agent of the Inquisition found out what was going forward. He heard that * These pious men were martyrs in the cause of truth : the first was burned in Smithfield, July, 1553 ; the other sufiered the same dreadful death in Portugal.

[172] a learned Englishman was in the city, and that some printers had been heard to say that soon all England would become Protestant. This man thought he would find out what all this boasting meant. So with much craft he made friends with the printers, and invited them to his house. Here he well sup plied them with wine. In the midst of their mirth they made known the secret, that some hundreds of copies of the New Testament in English were in the press, which were to be secretly carried over the seas by the merchants. The next morning the printer's house was surrounded by officers, and the press was seized ; but not before Tyndale, warned of the danger, ran to the rescue of his printed sheets, which he threw into a boat, and pushed his way from the shore. Sailing up the river Rhine he soon came to a safer place of labor. Often had the small ships of those days passed along this famous river with the wares and wealth of the merchants of Germany, but never did one carry so rich a treasure as was in the boat which conveyed Tyndale and the Bible sheets to the city of Worms.

After great pains, and cost, and toil, the last sheet of the New Testament was completed. Fifteen hundred copies were printed—a large edition in those days ; and now the bread of life seemed pre- pared for the people of his own dear native land. English merchants took charge of the books, and carried them to England along with articles of [173] commerce. The precious volume was packed in bales, and sent to London, Norwich, and Oxford. There they were readily bought by the rich, but though they were sold at a cheap rate, only a few of the poor could save money enough to purchase the holy book. Soon, however, they were found spread over the land, and many souls rejoiced in the Grospels and Epistles, which for the first time were held in their hands, and now cherished in their hearts. Some, on receiving a portion of the precious book, fell on their knees, and thanked God with tears of joy for ifc. When the Roman Catholic bishop of London was told that the printed books were coming fast to En gland, he was filled with alarm and anger. He soon sent out orders to make a diligent search among the merchants of London and the students of Oxford, for the forbidden work. Among the latter, some of those who were found to have it were thrust into a dungeon, where four of them soon died. Others were made to carry fagots of wood, and with them to kindle a fire, into which their own hands had to cast the books. As the flames rose into the air, the people were solemnly warned against the read- ing of the word of God.

But the hope of burning the New Testament out of the land was all in vain. The printer-priest kept working off more copies, and they were taken across the seas hidden in the corn which was [174] carried to England, at a time when great scarcity was felt. Thus bread to feed the body, and the bread of life for the soul, came in the same ships, and were together sent through the land. Decrees were issued against the possession of the New Testament ; the seaports and ships were strict- ly watched ; the warehouses and houses were search- ed; but still the blessed books arrived. Sometimes even Jews brought them over the seas. They came in pedlars' packs, and in boxes of merchandise — now in one way, and then in another. At length, the bishop of London hit upon a cunning plan, as he vainly thought, of putting a stop to the arrival of these books. He supposed, that if every copy could be bought up in the place where they were printed, the work would soon be at an end. A London merchant was engaged to do this business. Do your diligence to get them,'' said the bishop, and I will pay for them whatso ever they cost you.'' The merchant ordered his ship to be ready without delay, and crossing the seas, offered to buy up all the stock in hand. The bargain was soon made : the bishop had the books, the merchant the thanks, and Tyndale the money ! A few days after the books were safely in the charge of the bishop, a number of people were seen making their way along Cheapside and up Ludgate Hill. It was reported that there was to be a great sentence passed, to be followed by an'execution. As [175] they came to St. PauFs Cross, a large fire was send- ing up clouds of smoke high above the house-tops.

And now the bishop's ofiicers came with the poor prisoners—the Testaments, which were cast one by one into the flames, while a priest stood in the old stone pulpit in the open space, and loudly praised what was being done. But when all was over, many in that crowd could not but think how wicked and how shameful it was thus to burn God's holy book.

As a further proof of their anger, the priests seized Tyndale's brother, John, and one of his [176] friends. Then they set them on horseback, their faces turned to the tails of the horses, with bundles of New Testaments hung around them. In this manner they were made to ride through the streets of London, and on coming to St. PauFs to throw the books into the fire. But—how great the dismay—New Testaments were still brought to England ! The bishop soon sent for the merchant, and cried, How is this, sir ? Did you not promise and assure me that you had bought them all?" Yes,', was the reply; I bought all that then were to be had, but I per- ceive they have made more since ; and it will never be better so long as they have the letters and the presses ; therefore it were best for your lordship to buy them too, and then you are sure." The bishop only smiled at this answer, for he thought that, if he parted with more money, other letters and press es would be bought with it, and he should only serve to aid the cause he wished to crush. Finding how vain were all attempts to stop the circulation of the New Testaments, the next plan was to secure their author. Spies were sent over to decoy him to England. Though ready to sufier anything in his heavenly Master, s work, he would not willingly throw himself into danger. Craft, however, brought him into the hands of his enemies. While quietly pursuing his labor beneath the hospitable roof of an English friend, named Poyntz, [177] at the city of Antwerp, two wolves in sheep's clothing came to the house—one in the disguise of a merchant ; the other, who was a monk, was dress- ed as his servant. They pretended great interest in the doctrines of the Bible Christians, and were soon welcomed to their society. But Phillips—for that was the name of the pretended merchant—came to watch Tyndale, and, if possible to seize him.

One day, when Poyntz went some miles distant on business, a snare was laid for the noble reform er. Phillips called on Tyndale to borrow forty shil- lings, under the excuse that he had lost his purse on the road. They then agreed to walk out to- gether. There was a long narrow passage to go through, leading to the street. Phillips drew back, as if politely to allow his friend to go first, when two officers were seen standing at the door. Take your prisoner,,' cried the pretended friend, and in a moment Tyndale was in their grasp, while Phillips hastened to receive from the priests the reward of his treachery.

Tyndale was carried to a castle eight miles from Brussels, and placed in a close chamber. Here he remained for some time, but his faith in Christ made the gloomy prison a place of hope and of happiness to him. His way of life was so holy, that the other prisoners said, Well, if he is not a good Christian man, we know not in whom to 16 [178] trust." Through his teaching the jailer and his daughter were converted to God.

But once in the power of his enemies, nothing could save him from their wrath From that castle he did not come out till eighteen months had passed, and then only to die as a martyr.

At length, in October, 1536, he was condemned as a heretic, and ordered to be burned. On being fastened to the stake, he raised his eyes to heaven, and cried, Lord, open the eyes of the king of England.' ' His prayer was heard ; for, before three years had passed away, king Henry of England gave his consent to the circulation of the Bible, in the native tongue, throughout the kingdom. Thus per- ished this noble man, one of England's best reform- [179] ers ; as some one has said of him, " In putting the New Testament into the hands of Englishmen, he gave them the charter of salvation, the book of eternal life; while his own history affords a beautiful example of its purifying and saving power, under the blessing of the Holy Spirit." We pass on to another stage in the history of the English Bible. King Henry the Eighth began his reign as a good friend of the pope After a while, a quarrel arose, and he took the religious affairs of his king dom into his own hands. This gave rise to hope in the hearts of all Bible-readers: They now ex- pected to enjoy the truth unmolested. The king's favorite adviser, Cromwell, earl of Essex, was a friend to the circulation of the Scriptures, and he determined to have a complete edition printed in the English language. For this purpose he sent Cover dale, a pious and learned man, to the city of Paris, where the best printing was then done, to superin- tend the work. Although protected by the Eng lish ambassador, the pope ordered the printers not to proceed. The agents of the Inquisition were sent to seize the work; yet not till Coverdale, who before the storm burst on him had seen the gather ing clouds, had secreted a quantity of the half- printed sheets, and conveyed them privately beyond their reach. A large portion, however, fell into [180] their hands : some were burned, and as much as "four great dry vats fulF, were sold to a haber- dasher to lap his caps in.'' Coverdale fled to Lon don, where the book was again put into the press, and was, without further hinderance, Fynisshed Apryle, anno, 1539,', and soon had an extensive sale. From its size, it was called The Great Bible.'' The clergy were then required to provide one boke of the whole Bible of the largest volume in English, to be set up in the churches before Christmas." There were not many of the common people then who knew even the use of books. Any one who could read was deemed quite a clerk," and a little crowd would gather around him, while others sat or stood listening to the blessed truths of God.

Many persons who had the money bought the book, though it cost a very large sum. As a proof of the desire to possess it, a farmer, it is said, once gave a load of hay for two or three chapters of the New Testament. Many elderly people learned to read on purpose to peruse for themselves God's holy book ; and even little children flocked among the rest to hear portions of it read. Truly, the word of the Lord was precious in those days." At the death of Henry, his son, Edward the Sixth, succeeded to the throne. He began his short reign when quite a youth ; but young as he was, [181] he gave promise of great devotedness to the in- terests of true religion. On his coronation day, when he beheld the three swords used on such occasions, he asked where the fourth was. His lords looked up with surprise, and asked what he meant. ,' The Bible,', he answered; that book is the sword of the Spirit, and is to be preferred be fore these swords : without that, we are nothing, we can do nothing, we have no power.,' He loved the Bible himself ; he knew, from sweet experience, that its truths were precious to the soul. During his reign, which lasted only six years and a-half, the press was fully employed ; fifty editions of the Bible were issued ; and numbers of the people were nourished by its truths. But Mary, who next sat on the English throne, was a cruel bigot. One of her first law,s was to stop the people from reading the Bible. She had resolved to bring the whole nation back to Popery.

Then came dark days to England. Again people were called upon to choose between Bible religion and Popery ; and at what a fearful risk men chose the former ! It was the Bible and death ; yet there were not only men, but delicate women and chil- dren, who counted not their lives dear to them for the steadfast love they bore to the word of God.

Good John Rogers was the first of that noble band of English martyrs who at this time sealed their attachment to the Saviour by their blood. 16* [182] In spite of laws and spies, many a little con- gregation used to steal away into the thick forests, to lonely fields, to cellars and barns, to read the book of life. In Fox's "Book of Martyrs," we have a pleasing little picture of a pious company who went to the borders of St. John's Wood, then a wild and lonely spot on the north-west of London.

It was the morning of May-day, and, while their neighbors were dancing around the Maypole, they were engaged in listening to the word of God. But the constables, with staves and spears, broke upon ' them as they sat under the trees, and arrested them. They were all committed to prison, and soon after, thirteen were burned for hearing the word of God read, and believing its truths ! Everywhere the enemies of the Bible were on the watch. They cast into prison, or placed in the stocks, the faithful servants of God ; many of whofti, refusing to return to the Papal faith, were brought to the burning pile. Thus fell three hundred of England's best subjects — hest, because they loved and obeyed the word of God—victims to the bigotry of the cruel Mary.

After an unhonored reign, Mary died, unloved, and unlamented ) and her sister Elizabeth ascended the throne. There was a custom in these times, on the coronation of a prince, to release prisoners; whep this had been done, and men long bound came [183] forth to light and freedom, one of Elizabeth's lords said, There are yet four or five others to be freed." Ah, who are they?'' she asked. Matthew, Mark, Luke, John, and Paul,'' was the answer; "they have been long shut up, so that they could not talk to the common people, who are eager to see them abroad again." Elizabeth was a Protestant, and she was ready enough to let the good evangelists go free. Soon the cruel laws of her sister were re- pealed, and the books went out again among the people, who, as you may well suppose, received them gladly. A law was made that every parish church should be provided with a Bible, and that every parson should have a Testament for his own private use." How curious does such a law seem to us, when no minister, we should think, would be found without a New Testament in his study. Before the close of Elizabeth's reign, there were two hundred and sixteen editions of the Bible issued from the English press, a great many more than were published in all the other parts of Europe.

About one hundred years had passed away since good William Tyndale turned printer, that he might give his translation of the New Testament to his countrymen : now we come to an important period in the history of the English Bible. James the First became sovereign of England at the death of [184] queen Elizabeth. Shortly after the festivities at- tendant upon his coronation were over, a great council was held in the winter of 1604, at Hampton Court palace, a few miles from London. The ob ject of this meeting was to settle some church diffi- culties which had sprung up in the last reign ; but it is chiefly interesting to us on account of an im portant measure issuing from it—a new and able translation of the Bible; and it is the translation then ordered to be made that is used by us at the present time, and called the authorized version." The great work was done by many hands. Fifty- four of the most learned and distinguished divines were selected for this important business. These were divided into six companies, to whom were as- signed diff'erent portions of the sacred volume. The first met at Westminster, with the books of Moses, and all the Jewish history to the second book of Kings, for their work. Dr. Andrewes, whose learning was held in high estimation all over Europe, presided over this division. The second, under the charge of Dr. Lively, met at Cambridge, and they translated from Chronicles to Canticles. The third assembled at Oxford, under Dr. Harding; their portion was from Isaiah to Malachi. The fourth also met at Oxford, laboring upon the Gospels, Acts, and Revelation. The fifth, at West minster, translated the Epistles. The sixth, at Cambridge, undertook the Apocrypha.

[185] Each one of a division took the same chapter, and having translated it in his own study, they all met together and compared their work : if they did not agree, they altered it and improved it, until the best translation was agreed upon; it was then sent to the other companies for examination. After the whole was completed, it was carried to London, where some learned men from each university met and examined it anew; and these last learned doctors gave nine months' hard labor to the revi sion. A great deal of care and time and learning and study were thus bestowed upon this work, which have made the translation so valuable and enduring. In 1611, it was published as a noble folio Bible, which has been a fountain of life to thousands and thousands who read the English language. Blessed he God for a full, cheap, and free Bible, It is no longer a book shut up from the people — written on large sheets of parchment, and unfitted in weight and size for common use. It is not now lying only on the shelves of college libraries, cover- ed with the dust of ages. It is not bound and seal- ed by the cruel laws and wicked devices of popes and kings. We give thanks to God that the Bible is the birthright of every child in our land. We remember what we owe to the bold and holy men who set it at liberty, and gave it wings. We hold their memories in reverence for their courage and [186] fidelity in the midst of toil and opposition, and with exile and martyrdom before their eyes. We see them enduring all in hope and faith, that God's word might go free and bless the souls of men.

For this did many a martyr bleed, Tlie aoble and the brave, That truth its onward course might speed, 3Ien of all lands and tongues be freed, And life eternal have. We'll prize our blessed Bible then — What suflfering it has cost I What tears and groans of godly men. Who won it with their mortal pain, That we might not be lost. Shall we lay it on the shelf aside, And all its blessings spurn ? No ; deep within our hearts we'll hide Its truths, whatever may betide — God give us grace to learn ! What would Peter Waldo and Wyclifife and Luther and Tyndale say, could they now visit us, and see the Holy Scriptures in the hands of all people and even little children ! With what delight would they gaze on the poor man's twenty-five cent Bible and the Sunday scholar's eight cent Testa- ment ! And with what a shout of hallelujahs and hosannas would they look on the two hundred dif- ferent versions of the book of God, issued by the Bible Societies, in various languages of the earth ! But blessed are our eyes, for they see and our ears, for they hear those things which many prophets [187] and righteous men desired to see and have not seen them, and to hear, and have not heard them.

Matt. xiii. 16, 17. We behold the Bible in the pulpit, in the family, and in the school-house. There it is for all, and within the reach of all, and making known the message of God's love to all who will hear it. May we have grace to receive that message. It proclaims to us the delightful truth, God so loved the world, that he gave his only begotten Son, that whosoever believeth in him should not perish, but have everlasting life," John iii. 16. It makes known to us that a sinner is justified only by faith in Christ Jesus, whose blood cleanseth us from all sin ; who is able to save to the uttermost all that come unto God by him ; and who will not cast out any that do come. * It gives to us the promise of the Holy Spirit, whose grace and power convince us of sin, renew our heart, comfort us in distress, and make us meet for the joy and purity of heaven, † Let us, then, read the Bible with diligence, faith and prayer, and with a sincere desire to obey all its commands. And if there be those who would seek to turn us away from this blessed book, we will say wath that great and honorable man, Robert Boyle: "The Bible is a matchless volume: it is impossible we can study it too much, or esteem it * Rom. iii. 2.5, 26 ; 1 John i. 7 ; Heb. vii. 2.:) ; John vi. 37.

† John xvi* 7, etc.

[188] too highly." We will declare with the learned Sir William Jooes : "The Bible contains more true sublimity, more exquisite beauty, purer morality, more important history, and finer strains both of poetry and eloquence, than could be collected from all other books that were ever composed in any age or nation." We will say with the poet Milton : There are no songs to be compared with the songs of Zion." We will assert with that wise man, John Locke : "The gospel has God for its author, salva- tion for its end, and truth, without any mixture of error, for its matter." And with the renowned John Selden we will cry, There is no book in the world upon which we can rest our souls in a dying moment but the Bible." And whilst have a free and full Bible, and need not retire to the shelter of the forest to read its sacred pages, for fear of a dungeon or a cruel death, we will think of other lands where super stition and ignorance prevail, and hope and pray for the time when God's book shall be known through all the earth. Oh ! send God's holy book where'er Or winds can waft, or waters bear ; Let India's sons its page revere, Let Afric's land the blessing share. , Send it to where, expanded wide, The South Sea rolls its farthest tide ; To every island's distant shore, Mnke known the Saviour's grace and power.

[189] Seod it to every dungeon's gloom, Send it to every poor man's room ; Nor cease the woe-worn to befriend, Nor cease the heavenly gift to send. 0 Holy Ghost ! who gave the word, With thine own truth thy light aflFord, Give thou the quickening, saving power. On all the earth thy blessings shower.

Let grace thus turn each wanderer's eye To Him who did for sinners die, And sin and sorrow hence be driven, And earth be chang'd from earth to heaven.

17